good morning everyone
welcome to the 3-1-1 programming
language concepts
course uh hold on one second while i get
myself situated here
there we go a loud little heater going
on in the background there
uh so let's see can you guys hear me
okay
yes i just yeah great i just need one
person to confirm that's just great
thank you
um all right uh so you guys all took the
midterm
last week do you guys have any questions
about the midterm
i guess we should start out with those
questions first if there are any
questions
so this is only midterm correct excuse
me
this is the only midterm of the semester
right and then it's just the final
afterwards
okay we only have one midterm one
midterm and one final exam
all right well if you don't have any
questions um
you can also send me an email message
and i can answer them by email
um the scores were pretty good i was
pretty happy with the results
it seems like everyone's got a pretty
good grasp even though we're in the
kind of a weird online environment
everything's looking good
um so i'm gonna assume that you guys are
good with the uh
you know you're doing well so your
scores are reflecting it
i'm assuming there's not any problems if
you do have a problem you are
experiencing some difficulties with the
class
reaching out to me by email is a great
way of getting a hold of me
or creating a you know getting a zoom
session
scheduling a meeting with me would work
out just fine
okay so i'm going to take a look at the
course schedule
i just touch base because it's been a
while since the last time
i've seen you guys because last week was
the midterm week
um just as a side note we will not have
a zoom meeting
next week uh we will not have one
because
i will be uh navigating my way back on
campus believe it or not and
i am teaching a face-to-face class
starting next week on campus
and uh i know i don't know if i'm gonna
have internet access i don't know what
i'm gonna run into
and it's right after this class so i'm
gonna cancel next week's
meeting it's also st patrick's day and i
don't know if you guys are celebrating
st
patrick's day but next week on wednesday
is march
17th uh wednesday march 17th
i'm going to cancel that meeting because
i will be on campus
uh in the bbt building and i'll be
setting up for and
basically experiencing my first live
class
since the pandemic i'm so i'm really
excited about it but i don't know what's
going on
haven't been to campus in a year don't
know what to expect when i get there
i have a key for the door but you know
it might be locked
i have a problem and rather than having
you guys wait online for
for me to connect uh i would just rather
just uh just kind of cancel it and
test out the waters make sure i have
internet access and make sure
everything's working and then we will
regain
we will have another meeting on uh 3
24 and i'll do it right from the campus
so anyway long story short you don't
even know all those details but long
short story short we will not have a
meeting next week
so that i can make sure everything is
working properly
the classes for cs621 will be in person
for next week
that is correct uh karina
if you guys i know i do some grad
students in this class if you are in the
cs620
class uh and you're also in this class
uh which is kind of interesting um i
will be holding
this class via zoom in the 621 classroom
next uh not next week i'll be doing it
the following week
because i have no idea what i'm going to
run into next week
um so it'll be weird you can actually
show up early
if you are in the 621 uh
what do we mean that's gonna be
difficult if you're in the 620 cs621
class which is the graduate level
operating systems design class
and you have this class right before the
live
session i recommend showing up early
um i will be in the building at 11 00
am and i will be in that classroom at 11
am you can bring your computer
sit at a desk we'll have an online
zoom meeting and then we'll have the
live
6 21 meeting um
but next week we'll be kind of i'm going
to show up early next week and see
but i have a strange feeling i need to
all right i don't know about the
internet access i have to make sure i
have internet access i have to make sure
the logistics work out that building and
that classroom is not being used etc and
so forth so i'm going to try it out
experiment next week and see what
happens um
so i wish i could also come over
um yeah i think i'm gonna get in trouble
i don't think unless you're in the 621
the graduate class you can't
no i can't attend it live i ha
i will need to get permission for 3-1-1
students to show up
um but
you cannot show up yet so let's just
keep that one on the down low
and uh i know um i am missing college
too i'm missing
missing the face-to-face meeting so i
believe in a fall the 3-1-1 class will
be face-to-face by the way
and also my 621 class but anyway long
story short
uh i know i just gave you way too much
information
no class meeting next week for 311
because i'll be experimenting
okay so we are expected to have 50
percent of classes back in person for
those who don't know well that's good
thank you for that update so yeah while
we are discussing
that it's good to know 50 of the classes
will be back in person
that's good um apparently they need to
make sure we have enough capacity
uh because we're only allowed to operate
at 25 room capacity and
if you are in the 621 class and you are
showing up
uh not this semester fall semester fall
semester
next one uh fall summer
fall is 50 on face to face
summer is still 100 online
as far as i know just so you know
okay let's go back to our class so i
will send a message out at the end of
this meeting just to remind everybody
especially for those who did not attend
today
that next week's meeting will be
canceled but i will make it up for you
we will have a good meeting the
following week and i will have an
internet access and everything i just
don't like
just only you know unexpected issues
that happen
uh you know like showing up to a
building that hasn't been opened in a
year
i don't even know if i'm gonna have
anybody there to open the door
for the outdoor door for me uh so we'll
see what happens
i'm not optimistic but let's see
okay so last week was week seven today
is the 10th i believe it is march 10th
we are in week 8 of the class
you should be finishing assignment
number three which is due at the end of
this week assignment number three is on
scheme
uh the scheme programming language
assignment number four
is on a language called prologue and i'm
going to talk about prologue today
and i'll start the lecture on prologue
and i'll finish it next week
so the lecture that i'm going to cover i
just put up this morning
because i noticed it wasn't there it is
a review the lecture on prolog
programming called prologue.ppt
it is in the week eight materials right
at the top
right underneath assignment number four
so i'm going to go over assignment
number four
first and then i will go over prologue
i will start prologue today and then i
will finish it
not next week but the following week so
you have plenty of time the assignment
is not due until march
28th uh today is
actually the 10th uh next week is the
17th and then we have the 24th
it's not due until that week so we'll
have plenty of time between now and the
24th we are a little bit ahead of
schedule actually which is good
i had to go over prologue yeah i'm
thinking you're gonna find it quite easy
now there are some prologue lectures in
here these are not bad these are good
prologue part one
part two and part three you'll need to
know about prologue
from a fact and rule base but you'll
also need to know about the list
so the list processing in prologue which
is this list of pairs
so the last video has the list in it but
these are pretty small i would recommend
watching
all of them and also going over the
prologue that ppt lecture for example
so okay so let me switch over
to the assignment find the assignment
let's see here it is
that's what it is let's stop this one
and
we'll start prolog
i highly recommend using the swish
let me show that to you i just clicked
on the link that was in the assignment
i know i just started to share but let
me start a new share now
and it took me to the swiss swish
it's prologue and so you write the
syntax in this lower window down here
where i'm hovering my mouse
the output will show up over here as
well there's a ton of cool stuff in here
uh there's some prologue tutorials
there's some lists
so you can look at the list processing
over here and this is this is prolog
code on the left hand side over here
uh we have a little knowledge base uh
and i'll talk about what these things
are in a few minutes
some examples and then the examples
you'll see
puzzles you'll see
io machine learning graphical output
some ai
examples and so over here you've got all
of the
kind of code examples and tutorials and
things
and then over here is where you write
the stuff in and they have a little run
button here
and i'll run it this is just a fact this
is facts
uh that x a person loves mia
and that x is equal to vincent then
vincent
or x is equal to marcellus you know
uh in the database to see who who
actually look
and you don't know anything about
prologue yet so probably doesn't make
any
any probably does not make any uh sense
to you right now
um but the interface
is what i wanted to show you so let's go
back to the assignment
so you don't have to install anything if
you want to install something you can
install
swi prolog which is the same swi
prologue but it's not
running on the internet it's running on
your computer you'll get a screen that
looks very similar but you won't get all
of the examples
or the tutorial links as you do with the
swish online
so i highly recommend don't install it
on your computer just use swish
which is the online version of the swi
prologue
okay so the assignment goes through a
bunch of stuff
brief introduction to prologue
programming and prologue facts rules
i'm going to give you some powerpoint
information on this in a few minutes so
i'm not going to skip through that and
then your assignments towards the end
you have question number one given these
relations you're going to define some
new relations
and you're going to provide the facts
for father mother male and female
predicates and then test the entire
thing using prologue you'll know how to
do this once i go through the lecture
for number two you're gonna write a
relation remove an
element so it's an element
that is true if r is in the list
which results from removing one instance
of the element from the list
the relation is false if the element
isn't a member of the list
so you'll be removing an element from a
list
and this is kind of a function-ish
relation and then you're going to answer
the questions
what are all the answers to the
following queries
and and then you know it says ask
remove a from you know it's what is it
going to return so what are what are the
answers following queries and these are
basically queries that are run
using this relation that you're going to
create so you can run them and see what
the answers are
or you can guess at the answers and then
you're going to write a relation sub
sequence with list one list two that is
true if list one contains a subset of
the elements that are in ls2
in list two so so list one is in list
two
in the same order and then how many
different proofs uh for each one of the
queries
depends on um you know is a
d in the same sequence in here no
it's b a in here yes um
explain why there are so many or not so
many
and then write a prologue relation that
returns a list containing the union of
elements of two given lists you take two
lists and you put them together
and then write a relation anything you
want that does anything that you want is
not performed above
so you have these five questions to
answer and for this particular
assignment you want to answer
all five so i didn't remove any
to make it any easier for you because
these are pretty super duper easy
to begin with in the code you're writing
is extremely small
so keep that in mind
and let's talk about prologue so i'm
going to open up the
prologue.ppt unless we have any
questions about the assignment at this
point
until again prologue is really hard to
answer questions
all right so this is the logical
programming language
featuring prolog your new favorite
all right so prologue falls in the
category of
logic programming okay and you might
have noticed from looking at that
assignment
that the logic that we're using
can overlap into what i call functions
like a function it takes one list and
another list and puts it together
or a function that sees if list one is
part of list two
or returns true or false if an element
is actually in a list
which is the list processing you're
doing um
but they're functions but they're also
facts and rules
they actually instead of using all of
that vocabulary they call them relations
so it's like in the assignment the
wording you might have noticed the
wording looks a little funny
you see a relation what the what is the
relation
it's just another word for all this
other stuff so
we're not we don't call them functions
there's no such thing as a function
there's really no such thing as a it's a
list
really but there is a list it's logic
so prologue stands for programming logic
as you see in red here
pro and log so it's the most widely used
well okay it's like the only existing
logic programming language today
no there's no other ones out there so
it's the only thing you have
started in 1970s what is it good for
well oops
it is good for knowledge representation
i'll talk about that if you natural
language processing believe it or not
rubik's cube solving problems state
space
problems expert systems deductive
reasoning and deductive databases and
agents the main idea is you ask the
computer a question and it solves the
problems using principles of logic
okay i always say remember the eight
ball
and a magic eight ball that wasn't using
any programming that was just you know
whatever floated to the top
but you took the vial and you shook it
you said is it going to rain today
and the magic 8-ball comes up this is
highly likely
man that's prologue so you put a bunch
of data
into the database system or into the
prologue knowledge base
and then you ask prologue a question you
can ask it the same question you could
say is it going to rain today
a prologue can come back and say yes it
is or
no it's not most prologue systems they
don't come back with
you know try again later or highly
unlikely
or highly likely it's just yes or no
uh so you can sort of consider prologue
sort of like that magic 8-ball if you
have no idea what the magic 8 ball is
don't worry
about it you can google it later and buy
your family one for christmas
and uh you know they should be pretty
cheap at this point
uh because they're like an old old old
little
toy from the past kind of a retro toy
the main idea though is the same so the
program states the known
facts you ask it a question you make a
statement and ask the computer to search
for a proof that is true
and then the additional mechanisms are
provided to guide the search to find and
proof
let's compare this
okay so c c is an imperative programming
language
prologue is a declarative programming
it's like okay imperative languages
are things that have assignment
expressions
variables iteration the programmer
designs the way the program is going to
run
and it runs the same way every time you
run it well
give or take a few event driven
statements of code that you could put in
but for the most part your c function
runs like your c
function your main function just runs
the c commands in the same order every
time you run it
in a declarative programming language
you make
declarations so you don't have a
predetermined flow of execution through
the program
instead you ask it questions and it
answers you in a symbolic language form
so prolog is declarative you make
declarations
and i'll show you some examples of these
in a few minutes but declarations
generally come out in the form of facts
and rules
which is part of what the concept of a
knowledge base is
okay so the logic is non-procedural
it doesn't go from one line at the top
of the code to the bottom of the code
when you write the database you're
populating it with things and the things
you're populating it with
are relevant facts and rules even the
list
is a fact and the list processing is a
rule
the method of inferences whatever is
desired to produce the results
it's based on this predicate calculus
kind of concept and i'm going to come
through an example or two in a few
minutes that will show you
what this actually means and here's sort
of the way that you write the statements
you
they're called horn clauses and i guess
you'd have to go back to discrete math
uh yeah i think this is just great math
uh where you get like boolean
boolean algebra stuff and you get horn
clauses like so if
a one and a two and a three then h
so h is the head the body is a1 and u2
so if x is this is how the logic goes so
if x is positive and y is negative
then y is less than x
i think that's discrete math and prolog
is written like
this and we sort of saw that because it
was a sample that was
running on the swish interface
where we make this and this thing is
called a proposition a proposition
is a logical statement that uses a
relationship
but there's no value to the actual words
so man john likes pizza and
baseball they're called funktors
it's kind of like a function but they're
not really a function
and then what's in the brackets are
parameters
but mostly these are i call them just
you could just call them facts
the fact of the matter is that john is a
man
and pete's and john likes or people can
like pizza and baseball
and then we put these facts together and
they might consist of two or more
of the logical connectors for example we
have like the negative
not a or a and b a or b
this is definitely discrete math a is
equivalent to b
a implies b b implies a implication
equation
conjunction negative all of the
different possibilities that
are part of the foundation of predicate
calculus you don't really have to do
too much math to figure out the kind of
formulas to use because you're only
using all of them all over again it's
like maybe half a dozen like six ways of
expressing it
variables appear in the formula but only
when introduced by qualifiers
so for example for all women are
human there is no sport that bill likes
and this is not prologue code over here
uh this is just an illustration of the
concept of the qualifiers
i'm going to show you some code in a few
minutes there's a resolution and then
there's unification
there's forward and there's backward
reasoning so what we're talking about
now is the reasoning system
so you type in a bunch of facts you type
in a bunch of rules
and then you pick a reasoning system and
the reasoning system
by default is selected by the
interpreter so your runtime interpreter
let's say in
python is reading each line of code
and it is executing
whatever it is the user wants you to do
you say you write code in python very
similar to write code in c
line by line and it's running in
sort of a pseudo-imperative kind of
fashion
in prolog you put a fact in it's like
okay here's a fact
put another factor here's another factor
there's another factor there's another
fact
and the interpreter is keeping track of
where where are the facts
where the lists where are the rules you
know and there's all these categories of
things that you're putting into the
system and you're populating it
which is called the knowledge base and
then the runtime's job
is to provide the resolution and
unification
so resolution is how do we deduce from
multiple horn clauses
the answer how do we solve the problem
so the
compiler aka interpreter
is solving the problem for us
so we give it a problem and it solves
the problem so if the head of the horn
clause
let's say number one matches one of the
terms and then whole class number two
then when we replace them in the body
and the clause number one
and yeah yeah you don't really need to
do that the interpreter is doing it for
us and how do you determine when the
hypothesis
are satisfied is when you get a match
when there's some sort of substitution
that makes sense
so if you can substitute in data facts
into rules follow the rule
to find another substitution and you're
asking if that substitution exists
and if it's found the prologue system
can come back and say yes
if not then it says no let me give you a
little example and then there's an
example on the screen
but let me give you one actually let me
go through the one on the screen i'll
give you
another one that makes more sense the
resolution this is we're talking about
the resolution to resolve
the problem it's an inference rule
that allows us to infer propositions to
be computed by a given process of
position so suppose we have two
propositions
b implies a and d implies
c and then a is identical to d
and suppose they're going to be name a d
is t
then here we can infer that b implies c
all right let me give you something in
plain english
all tall people so just this is not true
i'm just making some crap
up here all tall people like
pizza bill
is a tall person does bill like pizza
yes yes phil likes pizza because all
tall people
like pizza mary is short does mary like
pizza
no okay
all people who like pizza
also like baseball
john likes pizza does john like baseball
prologue can say yes all right simple i
know very simple
very simplified okay imagine more
complex
logic with multiple different
levels or layers for example
it rains outside when there is a high
level
of precipitation as
is a fact high level precipitation rain
low level precipitation no rain
clouds in the sky rain no clouds in the
sky
no rain um temperature
above 70. no rain
temperature below 50 possible rain
could rain um
the months of the year you know january
february march april may
with their associated rain values
likelihood of rain yes or no and then
you ask the question
on march 17th is it going to rain
and then prologue would come back and
say yes actually training right now in
campbell
so i can say yes but why did it say yes
well because he goes back and says well
in march there's a highly likelihood of
rain
if there's cloud and there's clouds in
the sky okay there's rain so it's
it might you know need more information
it might come back and say
uh no and says well there's clouds in
the sky
and it's march and the precipitation is
high
and the temperature is low then prologue
can come back and say yes
so it's just the way humans think and
it's used a lot
in artificial intelligence and for
natural language processing believe it
or not to come out
and to formulate a response to a
question
from a bot or from some sort of a
logical inference that might be made
so unification is the process of finding
values for variables
during the resolutions so that the
matching process can succeed that's what
i just did it was unification by saying
it's march today is on march 17th but
today is march 10th
i have to say i'm stuck on the 17th you
know
i can look it up and i can use
unification
to find a correlating fact
to contribute to my resolution process
and instantiations temporary binding of
a value
and type to a variable to allow the
unification to happen the variables
instantiate
only during the resolution process
anyway there's a lot of
stuff you don't really have to know but
it kind of explains
how the prologue engine kind of works
all right so i'm going to kind of skip
ahead you can read this on your own a
little bit here i'm just going to kind
of skip ahead past the terminology and
go right into the syntax
okay we have a goal we have a query
we usually have a question mark at the
front it tells the prolog interpreter
see if it can solve and prove a problem
okay we have facts
rules and queries so in the first one
you have a family tree and i'll tell you
that the first
question on the homework assignment is
actually answered in this lecture
it's answered in the lecture further
down the road here
and i'm going to get to it momentarily
and i'll show you the answer before
this meeting is over just in case you
want to work on that assignment
next week and we don't we haven't
finished the lecture yet
so we have a collection of effects and
rules that's called the knowledge base
so it's kind of like um
it's kind of like human learning and if
you look at it from an ai perspective or
a machine
learning perspective it represents the
brain
the human brain so for example um
we go through life memorizing things
and then we go through life learning
rules
and we constantly ask ourselves
questions to navigate through life
you know for example uh everybody's
learned the rule of what hot and cold is
and everybody has learned the rules of
which items are associated with hot and
cold
so as a baby everybody burned themselves
at least one time
and you froze yourself at least one time
so you could feel
what he felt like actually a
psychologist say this is true
everybody has burned themselves one time
how do you how do you know what hot is
if you haven't burned yourself
either you touched the stove you touched
a candle you touched something
to feel the heat okay
now what you can do is new things come
in that you haven't seen
before you can relate them and put them
into categories
and this is learning theory so let's say
you were a baby and you burn yourself on
a stove
and then there's this big old pot of hot
water
and you see a similar you see similar
traits like you see steam
coming up from the water like you saw
steam on the stove
you see redness you feel the sensation
of heat
your brain should tell you don't touch
the water it's hot
or better yet you see a candle and you
see a flame or a fire
your brain is supposed to tell you
through its queries that
that fire is hot and you're not supposed
to touch it
and if that is true that's your
knowledge base
and your knowledge base is able to
answer
queries for you automatically as you go
through human reasoning and human logic
so a smart person doesn't touch
things that are hot because they're
going to burn themselves
so you don't go around constantly
touching things and
yeah you got the baby here too this just
never learns it's kind of like the
people in prison
when you say you're not supposed to
steal
you're not supposed to kill people
you're not supposed these are all the
rules that you're supposed to learn but
you keep breaking the rules
because you have some other form of
justification
for breaking the rule that it doesn't
make any sense to the
reasonable accepted rules and so you end
up in prison
or you end up burning yourself or
getting yourself into danger because
you're not following the rules correctly
so the rules in the knowledge base
for a human are to make you a functional
adult in
prologue it's to add richness or value
to the knowledge base so that we don't
have to be
experts on a particular subject area we
just go to the knowledge base
to acquire the knowledge so that's the
art of this style of programming
called logic programming programs are
called law uh knowledge bases
so you use prologue by posing queries
like should i rob the bank should i
touch the hot stove
should i and these are the kind of like
life queries that you might think about
okay so using a knowledge base we have
some facts we have woman janet woman
stacy
plays flute stacy we ask for a lot of
women stacy your prologue answers back
yes because there's a fact in the
database that says woman
stacy place do
this place the place flute stacy then
prolog comes back yes plays sploot mary
and it comes back are you kidding me and
now it does and it comes back and says
no
unless you program it to come back and
say are you kidding me
so i say it's kind of like the eight
ball shaking that april around and it
comes up with these various answers but
unlike the eight ball prologue is a
little bit more reliable
so you could ask roblox some questions
and this is a predict it's called
predictive systems
you can ask prologue some questions and
then roll i could come back and say
you know maybe highly likely
because it comes out the correlation
you're like well what kind of examples
of this type of programming do we have
in the real system
in in a real world
and then you look at this and you go
well what about those prediction systems
users who liked this movie this movie
and this movie
are gonna like this one over here so if
you've ever been in or
looked at netflix um most people i know
in the pandemic have
totally ventured out into streaming uh
netflix
is a good example of a recommendation
system
um we watch a movie and it tells you
uh you have a because you watch this
movie
you're gonna like these other movies
that's prologue that's logic and how's
it doing it's keeping track of
everybody who's watched the movie how
long they watch the movie and there's
some other analytics in there too
this would all be kept you can do a
prologue database to do a recommendation
system and there's a ton of them out
there actually
sample recommendation systems that say
you know because you watched
um i know now this movie
x y and z you're also going to like this
other movie
and then actually believe it or not uh
netflix uses a little bit of statistical
analysis in there because it says
there's a 98
match i always look at that and go a 98
match you're gonna like this movie and
i'm thinking well why
it's because i watched that other movie
but maybe you watched only like two
seconds of the other movie well
netflix is smart enough to know if
you've watched the movie from
start to end or did you watch just the
first five or ten minutes or get halfway
through the movie
it also keeps track of how far you've
gone through series
suddenly people binge watch on tv series
and movies all the time you go and you
just one episode after another one after
another one you spent all day doing that
well netflix knows you're doing that and
it keeps track of
the speed and the frequency in which
you've been watched it
binge watched it how far you got through
it
and then that's what comes up with this
category called binge worthy
these are the ones that people have been
binged watched for the longest duration
of time and have made it
past the 50 point or so in the series
so it knows which ones to put into which
one of the categories and it's using the
user's
behavior to predict that
so it's kind of interesting if you have
more than one user in your household
who is clicking on stuff and using stuff
that's going to cause a problem if you
create multiple accounts as you probably
know you can
then your stats and your prediction
system your prologue
logic base is going to be kept
separate for each one of the users so
it's a little bit more reliable in terms
of predictability
music through spotify through some of
the other applications are done this way
as well
where it keeps track of what what types
of songs you listen to
what's the beats what's the style and
then it will recommend
other songs that fit into that same and
it's not necessarily a label
genre it's a characteristic that's being
kept
about the particular track of music
you're listening to
google keeps track of this information
as well
these are used knowledge bases and
inference engines
and logical programming is used all over
the internet
and people come into this class think oh
i've never heard a
well prologue highly likely that you
have it it's probably one of the
it's the first and only logic
programming system out there
and it's being used in industry believe
it or not um whether you'll use it
if you get into artificial intelligence
or machine learning
or knowledge based programming expert
system programming
then you might get into it for example
triage medical triage systems
are generally programmed with logic
programming for example
a person comes into the hospital and
there's a bunch of questions on the
computer screen that the
uh check-in nurse needs to record you
know do they have a favor
do they have are they running you know
uh are they standing or were they
brought in a wheelchair or whatever did
they walk in are they bleeding
i don't know you know i'm not a medical
person but all of the
you know the things that would be
recorded and usually it's those
questions that you're being asked when
you walk into the emergency room
uh and then there are persons putting in
then what community so students
putting in computer science and says
okay put a red
band on them put a orange put a
yellow wristband on them or put a green
one on it
and the color is determining how
critical your case is
and so the different colors you'll get
care a little faster they're not going
to make somebody with a brain aneurysm
wait the same amount of time as somebody
who just walks in with a common cold
so yeah and it's a it's a resolution
system to see
what's really raining now just to see
what's uh
what category you fall into so the facts
here are propositions that are assumed
to be true such as
female janet male steve brother steve
janet
so they have no intrinsic semantics
which means the words don't mean
anything
the word male the word female the word
brother actually
doesn't mean what it means in english
and so some people like to write them
with
like f and b or
just make up words or use a foreign
language for it if you want
it doesn't mean anything just so it
doesn't have any
english meaning so
the rules combine the facts together to
increase the knowledge
system for example and this is read
backwards actually
male child of x y
is the sum of x y
so x is the sum of y if x is male
and x is also a child of y
it's a child of x y and
it's a male child of x y then they're
going to be a sign
so sine of x y and this is this believe
it or not it's supposed to be an
arrow and the arrow is pointing this way
so this is the tip of the arrow and
these are the two sides of the arrow
so but you know what computer programs i
don't have the keyboard doesn't have an
arrow has a colon an
minus sign which is the arrow
and it's red backwards so male x and
child of x y if it's a child and he's
male then he must be a sign
that's a rule this is a rule and you're
combining facts together so you have a
fact about male x
you have a fact about child x y oops
didn't mean to do that
and you are combining it together
to come up with a rule and you're going
to call it sun if this case
exists then it's going to be assigned
and then you substitute
so you put the rule in there and you
substitute the facts
into the rules and then you can come out
with a pretty sophisticated database
so here's a rule the rule statement
takes on the form of the consequence
equals the antidote so the consequence
must be a single term
which is the rule while the antidote can
be multiple for example
parent xy is equal to a mother
ex-wife or leads to a mother so a mother
ex-wife is a parent
a father xy is also a parent of x y
grandparents are parents of parents
so a parent can be a grandparent
and parent a male and a parent female
can be grandma grandpa
parent
and so the goal whoops
and you know i'm going to flip ahead for
a second because i remember i wanted to
show you something
i'm going to come back but i want to
show you something here
so in the first question
of the assignment let me go back to the
first question of the assignment
you find the assignment
there it is
we have a father a mother a female a
male
we have these are the rules given these
are given for you already
and the syntax has a dot at the end of
it you don't have to put a dot
at the end what you're going to do is
define
sibling sister grandson or descendant so
you're going to write one two three four
more rules
that provide for the these are facts
here
fact that x is male a female is
x mother is x y x is the mother of y
and x is the father of y
and you're going to put together what a
sibling is
what a sister is a sister is a
female sibling so
a sister and a sibling work together and
these rules can work together and you
can make up more
facts if you need to so you can go you
know a sister
is a female also female x
of a mother and a father
which is actually or grandson
which is the parent level so you can
actually make a hierarchy if you want
in terms of a structure but let me show
you from the powerpoint slide what this
is talking about
and this is a slide 30 of the powerpoint
it's giving you grandparent okay so
you have to tell you that it is actually
so
consider this database we have a mother
betty janet
we have a mother betty steve we have a
mother janet adam
father steve dylan we have a parent
that is defined by a mother we have a
parent that defined by a father we have
a grandparent
that has a mother and a father in it
parent xy and parent y z it's a
grandparent
and the goal is here to find the
of x adam well then the system
is going to run through a bunch of
iteration here prolog proceeds by
attempting to match the goal clause
with a fact in the database so it
matches the goal with
grandparent xz where z is instantiation
of atom
and what i want you to do is kind of
take this it starts on slide 30
and uh at your own pace take and come
through and see if you can
follow the logic there's a mother in
here
there's believe it or not you can
actually easily define
sister in here as well as brother in
here
but what i wanted to show you is this
tree that comes out of it this is the
grandparent x
atom and so this is why i said you can
actually take
and on a like a scratch piece of paper
and uh create a tree from this
to map out the logic and the logic in
this tree
is going to run through the the
implications
of the different lab levels um
i need to put you on hold for a second
because i just noticed there's somebody
knocking on my front door
uh i'm just gonna leave this right here
for a second
i will be back in one minute here
you
all right sorry for the interruption i
am back hopefully you guys are still
there i wasn't going too long
this would definitely not happen in a
face-to-face classroom
and i can't wait to get back into a more
professional environment for this
uh but anyway uh it was my amazon
delivery of why
wrong address basically so i wasn't even
taking care of my stuff it was for
somebody else
uh so let's see what do we have here old
memories
anyway let's just check in the chat i
saw something in the chat anyway so
solving for grandparent x adam
we could map it out and we could
substitute the rules in
and what i want you to do is on your own
time you know when you have more time
you're sitting there take a look at
slides number 30
through slide number uh
35 there's about five slides and see if
you can figure out the logic that is
associated with the substitution and how
the rules work this will help you with
assignment number
uh with the question number one that
asks you to define sibling and then
what you're doing is you're instead of
mother you're defining a sibling
so this will help you sort of and it
really does take a slower
look to see how the substitution works
and how
sub goals are created and how the goal
is satisfied
by substitution of the sub goals
so now i want to go back to up here and
talk about the forward chaining and
backward chaining
that is associated and i think i will
stop and do
the lists uh next time but we'll see how
far we get
so we have the knowledge base we have
and we went through this example already
we went through the rule okay so it kind
of uh the rule itself and this is the
grandparent rule
so we this is actually what this is
actually the question
this is one of the questions you have to
do a grandparent
so we're talking about the goal the
goals of proposition that we want to
satisfy to either prove or distribute
there's two ways of doing it
you can do forward chaining or backward
chaining
prolog by default does a forward
chaining mechanism and this is something
you do not have to
program into the system this is
something the system does
for you so this is what the compiler is
doing for
you it's creating the chaining mechanism
to apply the facts to the rules to
deduce the answers that are going to
come out of this
given the particular information that
you provided so the elements here you
should ask prolog the virtual machine
questions closed at the prompt so son
bob harry if it's in the database it's
going to come back and say
yes king bob france no
so it just comes back with yes or no and
you combine answers to questions
to variables for example who is bob the
son of
x is equal to harry and then your son
bob
x who is male x is equal above
and so is bob the son of somebody
you put a underscore in there to leave
it it's kind of a blank but it's not a
blank it's an
underscore to say that it's a
substitution
so no variables are really bound and
it's not really
using the variables it's substituting
values in
to perform the propositions and the
logic
for the particular cases all right let's
talk about backtracking
and forward tracking so how are
questions resolved here
we have son x harry so we can start with
a rule
so we could like say you know for
example to go backtracking you start
with a rule
and then you apply the facts to it
versus forward chaining which is bottom
up
starts with each rule and checks for the
facts
so that's like the same let me give you
a backward versus
the forward and back back tracking
uses what's called a forward chaining
technique and it does it from the bottom
up instead of the top down
so backtracking versus forward
tracking or two different directions so
let me give you an example backtracking
let's start with backtracking i'm
talking about that tracking right now
i come up with a conclusion and i say it
is going to rain today
and i tell uh prologue it's going to
rain
i make a determination that it is going
to rain today
so what it does is come back and say yes
or no
so i'm starting with the conclusion
instead of asking prologue
is it going to rain today
so you're starting at two different
directions i'm starting with a
conclusion when i'm doing backtracking
and so prologue by default does
backtracking
using a forward chaining technique which
i'm going to get into momentarily
so it starts with a conclusion like uh
bob likes pizza
yes or no versus does bob like pizza
or what sport does bob like
forward chaining fortune is a lot harder
to do
because we don't know it has to exhaust
more of the database
if i said what sport does bob like
we have to go through the entire
database to see how many times is bob
in there and what sports does he like in
there and how are we going to figure out
which sport bob likes
versus saying bob likes pin
uh paintball uh pig balls when he likes
playing with paintballs or he likes
baskets let's just say basketball
he likes playing basketball so we look
just for basketball and see if bob's
associated with basketball if he's not
it's a clear answer no he doesn't so it
depends on whether you're going to start
with a conclusion
or you're going to start with a
hypothesis so like if i say
you know it's going to rain today or
it's not going to rain today and if i
said probably it's not going to rain
today
it's going to come back and say no
because it is raining right now actually
it isn't campbell all right
i live in campbell by the way
uh so you know what when you go back to
when i go back to campus i
will have to actually commute but the
roads aren't too bad these days
so unless it's raining i can ask
prologue is the commute going to be bad
that's forward chaining by the way and
it comes back and says yes
or no prologue could come back and say
if i ask for a log i'm going to do
another example
forward forward prologue is it gonna be
a
long commute prologue could come back
and say
no because everybody's staying home
right now
if i said a backward approach prologue
the commute's terrible
problem can come back and say no it's
not terrible everyone's staying home
right now
so don't get too concerned with it i'm
not gonna ask you anything like that on
an exam
but it's just understanding that there
are two directions kind of helps you put
it into perspective
the prolog database has already
been configured especially the one
online and there's no way of changing it
it's going to do it backward tracking
uh it's going to do this exactly right
here from bottom up
so it starts with each one of the rules
and then checks for facts
so using the database systematically
generating new theorems until one
matches
the query that is found so father bob
mann is
equal to father given the gold man bob
under forward chaining father bob is
matched against father
x to derive a move back to man bob in
the database and in fact satisfies the
goal and so we can come back and say
yeah
and bob is a father
if he's in the database that way
backwards chaining from a top-up
perspective starts with the facts
and uses the rules that apply use the
goals to work backwards to the fact
given man bob as the goal you match
against man x to create a new goal
father bob father bob the goal matches
pre-existing fact
does the query is also satisfied satisfy
both directions so it doesn't mean that
forward
or backward top down versus bottom up
is going to produce any different
results for you it's just a different
systematic approach
so for example i could ask the question
you know no unless i get talked about
rain anymore
uh is csu east bay going to open back up
again
or when is csu east bay going to open
back up again and i thought we're going
to
if i were a prologue i'm not really
guessing if i had logic in my system
to figure this out i'd say well alameda
county
what tier are they in and if
in the database it said tier purple and
then there was a rule in a database that
said
in the tier purple no online class no
face-to-face classes can take place
then i would recently deduce that no csu
east bay is
not opened up but if the tear changes to
tear red
and i ask the same question the system
might come back and say yes
they are because they're interred the
difference though
is that prologue doesn't tell you the
because
it doesn't tell you that because it will
just come back and say yes or no
it's kind of like does bob like
chocolate well we don't know if bob
likes chocolate
but in the database if bob likes cake
and all cake are chocolate and bob likes
donuts
and all donuts are chocolate and bob
likes ice cream and
all ice cream is chocolate then probably
would deduce
that bob likes chocolate because all of
these other things
have chocolate in it which is
kind of like how people figure out what
they like or they don't like
if you think about it which is kind of
funny because people have weird
food preferences because sometimes i
like something
i have uh well my sister actually claims
she doesn't like eggs
however she eats a lot of foods that
have eggs in them
so i'm thinking how could you say you
don't like eggs that's logically
incorrect
when you're eating like omelettes that
have eggs
sorry you know it's like wow it's like
saying you don't like cheese but you eat
pizza with cheese on it how could you
say you don't like
cheese so it's prolog
can't make those mistakes because it
only knows
what people like and don't like if you
put it in as a fact
i put it in prolog database that's the
fact that
this is a prediction system you can
predict what kind of pizza barb would
like
because we could say barb likes ham
barber likes pineapple barb likes cheese
broth likes red sauce barbecue
i can't prologue what kind of pizza does
barb like
it can come back and tell me you want a
hawaiian pizza
or you want meat lovers pizza or you
want
so which is actually kind of funny
because some of the pizza companies do
this
i tell you well click some boxes here or
when you sign up for services it says
you know what kind of music do you what
stations do you listen to
what kind of music do you like and then
it makes some recommendations for you
that's prologue that's a great example
of a prologue database wine pizza is
like
stabbed in the heart for italians yeah
it is
it's not really italian yeah i like you
know you guys are making me hungry now
because i think i'm gonna actually order
pizza for lunch
anyway yeah um barb does like hawaiian
pizza by the way
yeah okay forward and backward chaining
that's what i just described here we
have bottom-up resolution for
chaining our top-down resolution
backward chain and that's the other
thing
that's the other thing that prolog can
also be programmed to look at
all right we're all different ages
we're definitely past the age of five
years old however
hopefully everybody in the class is over
five
and i don't know around five-ish the
theorists the psychologists say that's
when we start actually developing our
true memories of things
so up until like five or so
four or five is debatable but there's a
certain time when you're a baby
you keep going back and forth i like
this i don't like this i like this i
don't like this
and who knows what you like but around
the age of five you start developing
some
strong interests i like writing i like
listening all right just because you
liked something when you were five years
old that's the bottom of the database
and every year you're six you're seven
you're 10 you're 15 you're 20.
each year you keep adding more facts to
it
so then people change their mind when i
was five i didn't really like sushi
now that i'm older the topper
the higher levels of the likes when it
comes to food
likes sushi like not liking vegetables
and then liking vegetables
when it comes to food for kids uh
so the data changes in the knowledge
base
and if our brain is sort of like a
prologue knowledge base
then we're constantly changing the facts
and the rules
and so what is going to end up happening
here
is that we're going to we're going to
prove ourselves right or
wrong depending upon which direction in
the knowledge phase we're searching
so if i started from the bottom and i
said
okay do i like sushi i'm gonna come back
with no no
no no way at the top we're going to see
a yes
up there so here's ways of
creating it so that prologue continues
the search you just put a semicolon into
the
box it says okay i found a no a no i
know okay i got a yes i got a yes
because the facts have changed so it
depends on whether you're going forward
versus
backward in terms of the newest versus
the oldest facts
most databases will look at the newest
now this is the new information that's
on the top
not the bottom if you start at the
bottom you go all the way through the
entire history of your entire life to
see if you like something it's going to
change over time
if you look at the top you're going to
get a more accurate answer in this last
year do i like sushi yes
then i'm going to get a more definite
correct answer so a lot of people didn't
want to go through the entire database
and you're not going to search through
the entire database
you're going to look at the last the
most recent the most recent entries
okay so bottom up searches the database
from facts to rules and attempts to find
the sequence of matches within the
database to satisfy the goal top advance
starts with the goal
the backward chaining starts with the
goal the conclusion i call it a
conclusion
it's goal and then searches the database
to see if it can
be satisfied can we satisfy the goal is
it going there it's going to rain today
yes or no versus is it going to rain
today
so i'm not going to pick a side here i
picked the goal already and see if it's
true
here i find out what the goal actually
is so
the second part of the resolution is the
depth versus versus the breadth first
search and this is if you
have taken data structures and
algorithms and you know there's two ways
of searching if you're going to exhaust
the search tree
so this is the large search space
we're going to apply depth or prep so if
we do dab
we go all the way down you start at root
go all the way down
each one of the chains to the lowest
depth
of the tree to see if we can satisfy the
goal
versus breadth going this way the whole
level one
the level two the level three process
all the sub girls
parallel versus going down and seeing if
each one of the sub goals can be
satisfied
prolog designers went with a top-down
backward chaining
depth burst resolution process by
default
it does not mean you can't change these
things
if you this is an open source utility
open source
compiler you can certainly reprogram it
or change it
so that it does something differently by
default we're going to have backward
chaining
i'm going to see if the goal is true and
we're going to go debt first
because once we have exhausted one path
if one of the sub goals
does not exist the whole goal doesn't
exist
so if you're trying to find out if bob's
a father
but bob is not male we gotta
we're immediately gonna say no bob's not
a father
bob might be a mother if
we can't satisfy that one goal and we
can't satisfy be going through a debt
first we're gonna eliminate half of the
search space
constantly but why continue checking if
one of the facts is already wrong
so it proves to be a little faster
in terms of solving the goal
backward chances for uncle male sibling
here's a sibling for you
as a parent it's called backward
chaining and
you can go through the process on your
own it takes a little bit of
sitting and looking at it okay so i
already went through the little example
here
and we're gonna i'm gonna do the list
next time
uh if you wanna look ahead it's pretty
easy
you might actually if you if you really
wanna look ahead on the prologue
list uh so this is past the first one
and i highly recommend doing is pretty
easy
um here actually i'll just show you the
list real quick here
and i'll go through more of those
examples uh prolog lists are not too bad
they look like this they have these
square brackets
so append x and y
with one two three this is the append
predicate
they call it a predicate is it really
the syntax kind of he follows through
the head and the tail it's a link list
believe it or not
so consider the following angle head
versus tail so we have one two
three four head is one the tail is two
three four
so in developing the list here's a list
it has a square brackets
an empty list has nothing inside of it
so prolog
list consists of zero or more elements
separated by commas they can be
characters
numbers they can be anything uh they
could actually be a list
inside of a list just like prologue the
lists are not
stuck to just one data type
uh here's some examples the head could
be equal to one the tail can be equal to
two
three av so h matches the first element
in the list
t matches the rest of the list
you can ask it t one two three four it's
gonna come back and say yes because
the tail is one two three four the head
is one
all right the tail excuse me is two
three four
think of it as like linked list the
first element is the head the rest of
it's the tail
so here's a pen where we're going to
take this list and this list and append
it together to this list
so x is equal to 1 2 3 a b
because we have 1 2 3 and a b that's
going into x
do not think of these as
functions because they're not functions
think of them
as a list fact
so 1 2 3 comma a b comma
x takes x and makes it
into one two three a b because it's
appending and the function append
is actually built in by the way so what
you're going to do
with those number two through five
is use built-in functions to achieve the
goal
of what it is you're trying to do what
you're trying to accomplish so
to take two lists and put them together
that's really an append
actually so intent might help you with
the assignment
so to append these guys together x
is 1 2 3
a b and x is now
a and b
so take a look at these go through the
tutorials that are on the swishy site
when it comes to lists
you could google it on the open internet
but
uh there's some right wrong answers out
there
so i'm just looking at my time here
quick until 12 15. we do it's like about
10 right now i'm gonna stop because this
is really a two-part lecture
i will start at list not next week but
the following week
we will start here and i'm going to open
the floor for any questions you might
have
next week's meeting is cancel but
everything i'm giving you here in the
lecture is in those
youtube videos so you can work ahead go
ahead and watch the youtube videos
otherwise i will see you guys on the
24th for our next zoom meeting
so again no meeting next week because
i've got this
really weird transition to face-to-face
classes for the
class that starts like in 15 minutes
from now
um and so we will transition
and we will be up and running on the
24th
are there any questions if there
aren't then have an excellent day enjoy
the rain because prologue said it's
going to rain today
so it is raining
uh we need the we need the rain have a
good day
see you on the 24th
unless you have questions i'm going to
hang out a little bit thanks i will
enjoy my pizza
i'm actually going to water it right now
i'm going to order my pizza ah but
unless you guys have questions we're all
done for today
i'm gonna hang out until you guys all
log off before i log off just to make
sure we don't have anybody
trying to formulate a question in their
head
you guys are good katrina you good
yeah it's about the website the prologue
from which we don't need to um
install it i was just a bit confused
that uh where is it
let me share it actually
like for when i went to swish
you saw the screen
all right let me enlarge it so i can get
a better view
this stuff is in here because i hit the
run button you can actually close that
out
there we go yeah but mine shows an empty
one and the left side it says like
program in the right side i
kind of know how it goes but for the
left side
why because um i clicked on
first steps knowledge bases
see where is that located uh right to
the left or says welcome to swish
[Music]
in the examples
up in the left hand corner you'll see
something that says i have my mouse over
right now
it'll say examples and then if you click
on knowledge base
it shows you this knowledge-based stuff
you can actually do this you can take
this oh i see it and copy it
and stick it over here on the bottom
there you go and it's an example of the
vincent loves
mia marcellus pumpkin oh i hit the run
button
oh can't run the query do the syntax
error yeah probably cut and paste here
yeah uh syntax operator expected
instance um
yeah anyway i just i was just playing
around with it
okay okay i'll just try to get familiar
with this too
yeah you're gonna need to play around
with it i would go through some of the
examples example programs
and then the prologue tutorials are
really good
okay i'm using because when i first went
to the
website there was nothing there but now
that
uh you know i see the example click on
some of the examples to see some of the
stuff
i probably clicked on it the last time i
was on the website which is why i saw
stuff
okay yeah play around with it and if you
do have a running
problem like you always do you can
always email me as well
okay thanks okay have a good day you too
all right thank you i'm gonna log off