good morning everybody can you hear me
okay
i just need one person to confirm that
they can hear me okay good thank you
chris
thank you um so i am actually in
uh the csu east bay uh in a classroom
i don't know if i could i don't have two
cameras on this computer so i can't show
you so you're looking at the backdrop
of uh one of the classrooms i guess
there's a board i could use here
um but for the most part um i'm
on campus uh last week we did have some
technical difficulties so it was a good
idea that we did not have a
we did not try to do it well this is
better to try not to do a
zoom recording last week and because
it was uh it was quite difficult
actually to get the technology to work
uh but this week we're doing okay this
week we've got everything functioning
properly
and uh and back up and running
um so if you are in the osd course
that follows this one and you want to
connect in the classroom i've opened up
the side door so you can get in
but you have to be also enrolled in the
operating systems design course
only extended that invite to those
students everybody else still needs to
connect remotely
for the duration of the semester um so
before we get started are there any
questions comments or concerns
before i jump right in i'm going to go
over assignment number five today
well you can just speak up or you can
put it in the chat
uh your choice uh let's just see
let's see where is my assignment number
oh can't hear anybody
did someone talk
oh yeah oh did you have a question
sorry okay no problem it was just a
background noise
got it just checking
um i didn't i did have my speakers
turned down so
i couldn't hear you anyway one of you
are asking a question
all right so assignment number five is
what you're looking at right now
and uh let me just go to the classroom
real quick here let me stop this year
for a moment
[Music]
let me find the class
i'm using a different computer than i
normally use
but this one does work let's see it's
not my big old imac
uh let me share this one
moment there we go
all right and and we'll have probably a
pretty quick meeting today just going
over simon number five
uh but let's see
just given us a little view of the
calendar i can probably make this a
little bit bigger
uh but right now today is the
30th i believe no no today's not the
30th today is
the 24th march 24th uh which is in week
10.
next week you should know that we have
spring break uh so spring break is next
week
the 3 29 to 4 4
and uh there will be no class for the
entire week
because it's all it's spring break um
so we will not have a class meeting next
week so enjoy your spring
on spring break hopefully the sun will
come out it's actually a pretty nice day
here in hayward
uh but we're supposed to get some like
70 degree weather so
maybe you'll have some outdoor time
hopefully
but spring break will happen on 3 29 and
uh
well the week of 3 29 but you can still
turn in assignments and i will still be
available
so if you have a question you can always
send me an email message and i will
respond to it
i'm not going anywhere obviously so
uh so we're right now we're in week 10
uh today's uh 3 23 now today's 3 24
and uh i've got uh assignment number
five
that you're going to want to start
working on so let me go over that
assignment
uh you should be continuing and
finishing up on assignment number four
which is the scheme assignment
number five is on object orientation are
you in the three one one
ah perfecto okay good i just started it
i put it up on the screens too if you
wanted to but it's completely up to you
you can log into zoom as well
yeah all right
so if you've looked at assignment number
five you probably have freaked out
already
on it uh or maybe you haven't who knows
uh
so let me tell you a few things about
assignment number five first of all
there have
a shortcut alternative so you don't
actually have to do this assignment
so let me just repeat that so everybody
can hear it
you do not need to complete assignment
number five
as described in this document if you
want to complete
assignment number five as described in
this document more power to you i will
be going over it momentarily
but i would do the alternative
assignment
so what's the alternative assignment um
the goal of assignment number five
was to introduce you to the concept of
object orientation
so some of you have already taken
hopefully an object during the
programming course
it was a prerequisite for cs311
so most likely you have taken one um
and so in that class that you took you
probably learned c plus plus
or maybe java or maybe python
object-oriented python so the
alternative
assignment for number five is that
you're going to create
two programs the same program
but you're going to write it twice in
two different
object-oriented programming languages
and you can recycle one of them
so what does this mean and in your c
plus plus
class or your python class or maybe it
was java that you took
you wrote something for an assignment
maybe it was a fahrenheit the celsius
conversion program
and maybe it was a to-do list or
something he wrote something
and it had object orientation as a theme
to it for which she wrote a class
at least one class object so
you can take that program that you wrote
and write it again in another
object-oriented programming language a
different one
so it has to be a little bit you know
above hello world
like i don't want you to write hello
world twice that would be too easy
um you don't have to write the same
program twice if you've already written
it one time
and you can use any object or in your
programming languages
language that you want as long as you're
creating a class
so you need to create at least one class
and you do the same theme the same
program
or the same theme you do it twice in two
different languages
so you could do like java and c plus
plus or you could do
python and java or c plus plus and c
sharp or object any language that you
want it does not have to be a language
that is taught in this course
um because we're not really teaching
object-oriented language in this course
there's a separate class called
object-oriented programming
actually now it's with 401 some people
might be taking the
software engineering 1 which is 401 and
in there you're learning java
and you're practicing object orientation
in java
you might have done a very similar type
of class in c plus plus
you don't actually have had to have
taken a class in it either
you can experiment and explore brand new
languages on your own
you just need to pick two
object-oriented programming languages
write the same program twice and so in
doing so you don't have to provide
any documentation uh which means you
don't have to
do any write-up or provide any
scripts or text files or comparison or
contrast or anything
while you're writing the program and
performing the programming tasks
you will naturally discover the
differences in how each one of these two
languages varies on its own
so before i start in with the assignment
as described do we have and that
is not what i just what i just closed
was not yes
not what i just described do we have any
questions about the alternative
the alternate assignment number five
would you like us to um like add
descriptions of like the differences
between
our both programs
you can if you'd like but you don't have
to and if you're going to do that i
would just put comments in the code
okay you know like in like for example
in c plus plus uh there's a constructor
deconstructor and a copy constructor
in java there's only a constructor
actually that's true there's only a
constructor
um c plus plus there's operator
overloading
there's um actually c plus plus supports
multiple
and we're talking about object
orientation today so this is part of the
lecture too um
and i'm just gonna go through the the
differences in a few minutes but
just to give to continue with what i was
saying in c plus plus
um we have multiple line inheritance
like you can take
one class and inherit like five other
classes
and put them all into one class in java
there's a single line inheritance
but java also supports abstract and
interface classes
sc plus plus doesn't support python has
a single line inheritance
ish doesn't have interface or abstract
classes but supports the concept
the languages themselves although
they're all called object-oriented
programming languages they all support
object orientation
in different ways and the purpose of
writing
this assignment is really to explore how
these languages are different
in terms of their interpretation of
object orientation
if if it helps your understanding to
think out loud
and to write comments in the code about
the differences
that would be fantastic it's not
required because you're gonna i'm gonna
know that you know it
because you're writing the same program
twice and you're gonna know that
you know you can't do the same thing and
the syntax is different
the semantics are different and the way
the program runs is completely different
and you're going to just
notice the differences yourself just by
writing it
try to pick something that demonstrates
some of the differences which is why i
don't want you to do like a hello world
i want you to do something where it
shows
like maybe do a maybe do one of your
more advanced c
plus plus uh programs if you're going to
do it that way
that takes and inherits one class from
another
and then show how it could be done in
java
so what you're going to turn in is the
let's say you did
java and let's say you did python you're
going to turn in a
java file and a dot py file i don't need
to see the executable code
and you can make them as you know two
separate
you can upload multiple files for your
assignments
you can put them in a zip file and just
upload one file
or you can attach multiple pys or
multiple java multiple c plus
files and submit them all for the
assignment there's no explanation that
needs to be done
when i looked at the grading for this
and i take a look at the files i'm going
to see
hopefully i'm going to see two programs
in two different languages
for this and if i do have a question i
will ask you
um you want you can if you want put it
all into
copy and paste and stick it onto a word
file i've got some creative submissions
in this class
um but you just
want to submit the files i don't need a
word file that describes anything
i don't need any documentation i don't
even need you to tell me you're doing
the alternative
i will notice it that was a very good
question does anybody have any other
questions about the
alternative the alternate number five
so there's your value add for actually
showing and participating and
uh watching or watching the zoom
recording
you know about all of the um
different ways that you can do something
without having to do it the hard way
okay so while you're while i'm going
over assignment number five which is
what's going to be next i will you know
think
think of some questions you might have
if you'd like
and i'll pause for questions at the end
as well
of this here okay
i'm not discouraging you from doing this
assignment
however i'll tell you why it's in here
and i'll tell you what it's about and
i'll give you
some guidelines on it whether you do it
or not
completely up to you i usually have one
to five
students who actually do it um
and i will tell you if you do it it'd
probably be a worthwhile learning
experience
but i don't know how much time you have
in your schedule and i don't know
if it's a worthwhile experience that
you'll do now
or whether or not you'll just do it
later maybe if you want to for fun
i would only do it if you have a lot of
time available
and you want to really learn this stuff
it'll definitely teach you the
differences between
java and c plus plus the reason why this
is in here is because of the timing of
the assignment
it is the first assignment that's um
due actually or presented after the
midterm
and and usually when the face-to-face
classes were running around the midterm
and
really around spring break i lose
everybody
everybody disappears and then they show
up a couple weeks later
trying to catch up and so they don't
bother
going through the course materials they
don't bother listening to any of the
stuff they missed or you know back in
the face-to-face class they don't even
bother
figuring out how to catch up they just
pick up where they left off and they
take like three or four weeks off until
the end of the semester
so when they go back to go pick things
up they look at this assignment
and they don't know about the alternate
one i do it every term
they don't know about the alternate
instead they do this assignment
and this is the for five points this is
the worst assignment on earth
so as i go through it just think you do
not have to do this
but there will be people that will do
this because they don't
know that there's a substitution that
you can do instead
okay um and it's in there to reward you
for actually participating in the class
and knowing that there is a substitution
and plus this is just complicated anyway
you're going to compare if you do this
assignment you're going to compare java
and c
plus you're going to look at the text
file io
you're going to look at the support for
data abstraction class libraries random
number generator exception handling
string manipulation dynamic storage and
all a bunch of other stuff
okay this assignment is actually the
second
stage of compilation and it involves
semantic analysis
so if you remember assignment number one
in the course you did syntax analysis
you wrote a lexical analyzer that took
and read in a file
and that file parsed it out or
you know kind of alexa like syllable
lexical analyzed it out
made into lexa means that related to
tokens and you
put these tokens into different token
categories
and you
created created a
symbol table essentially as the output
so this one takes the symbol table
and creates random it says ran you're
going to create a random sentence
generator
and it's going to be to write notes
excuse notes
so we're down the professor's patients
well here's i need an extension because
these are some examples of the tactics
of these excuses complete innocence
honesty so you're going to have and
you're going to have to put this
together yourself
grammar so there'll be a grammar file
there'll be a list of or symbol table
that you have to create
of tokens and you're going to make
proper sentences and so instead of doing
a gener a recognizer
like a compiler does you're going to do
a random sentence
generator where you give it a bunch of
words you give it a bunch of sentence
types
and it produces sentences like for
example i'm sorry i can't turn in my
assignment my dog ate my
homework or you may it may put together
i'm sorry
my assignment is going to be late my cat
uh scratched up my homework
or i'm sorry or i'm not sorry or
pardon me uh my assignment's going to be
delayed by one day
because blah blah blah and so these
sentences would be randomly generated as
excuses
uh you don't have to use homework you
can use other things
the grammar can be an object a verb for
example the big yellow flowers
verb tonight a big yellow flower sign
ver
adverb tonight
so in your random sentence generator
classes
you're going to demonstrate if you
choose to do this
you're going to write two programs one
in java and one c plus you can write the
program
twice in two different languages it's
gonna
create these random sentences for you
you're gonna have a constructor in both
languages you're gonna have a random
sentence
uh method that's gonna return a random
sentence generated from the grammar
on the java end of the deal you're going
to do a two string
you're going to overload the two string
operator on the c plus plus you're going
to overload the
the c out operator and you're going to
do a distractor
to delete the dynamic memory that's
allocated as well
but you don't have to do the destructor
of course because there is no destructor
on the java which means you're going to
work with dynamic memory
on the c plus side of the fence
so you might use some library adts to
store manipulate the various components
of the grammar
and see in c plus you might uh
you know be storing symbol tables
or buffered information you're going to
expand the grammar to have a start and a
termination symbol
and pretty much what you're going to do
is you're going to match up
different parts of the second stage of
compilation
and maybe even you know generate
grammar abstract syntax trees or
grammar trees um to show the inputs or
to show the outputs or to show any part
of it
so it's very complicated so your program
should take one command line argument
which is the name of the grammar file
and then
uh an error message should occur if the
file's not found
and the output is that the program will
print out the grammar rules and three
random sentences from the grammar and
then exit
so long story short
the assignment is interesting
but it's a lot of work so if you've
already created something
in a programming language of your choice
that's object oriented
like c or c plus plus it would be much
easier i believe
just to write the same program again in
a different language
okay so if you do the alternate make
sure
that you actually have two separate
you have two separate languages okay so
we have a
question in the chat says can be a good
assignment to put on your get
yes it could be actually it could be
very good
uh if you do that assignment
and if you're thinking about taking
the compiler implementation course or
compiler design course which is a grad
level course
but we do have some grad students in
this class actually and
some students as the undergrad want to
take it because they want to get into
programming languages
and designing your own language if
that's your goal you might want to try
just doing the assignment
it's not as hard as it looks it's just
more complicated than the alternate one
there is some value added to doing the
um
i'm not discouraging anyone from doing
it i just think
that for five points it's a lot more
work than some of the
other assignments in this class um and
it's kind of designed that way
so before i move on do we have any other
questions
on the assignment number five
okay so well in the course materials
there's a little mini lecture here
and the lecture is on modern languages
and so i want to bring that up and talk
about
object orientation and i also want to
talk about modern languages for a few
here
so we're going to go um where do we go
from i wanna
probably stop about noon so we have
about a half hour here
um because i do have to get ready for my
other class today
uh but here we so go
kind of want to talk about this and as
i'm going through the lecture if you do
have some questions
about the assignment feel free to put
them in the chat we can still i can
still answer questions on that you can
also send me email messages too
so this one is in the course materials
under the current week that we're in
right now it's called
modern lings and the reason why i want
to bring it up is because we're not
going to look at these languages
in this class rather uh
let's see how do i get this out of the
let's see
i'll use slideshow
and here let's just go out of here
i'll just do it this way there we go
see if i can up there i go i can do it
okay
it's not really lecture 17 although it
is
labeled that way sometimes i move these
lectures around
um for different versions of the course
okay as i mentioned before
we have different object-oriented
languages and this week is really about
object orientation
and the implementation of these
languages is highly dependent upon the
technology and the
era for which they were developed so
c was the base language of c
plus as you all know and the c
programming language
is not it's imperative it is not object
oriented
so what the
community did was take a non-object and
language object-oriented language and
make it object-oriented and in doing so
they had to add these features to the
language that were
band-aids duct tape uh
makeshift not really appropriate
features
uh that were done that way
so that um the language could work
and so the concept of the destructor the
concept of the copy constructor
um oh it says my internet is unstable i
hope you guys can still hear me
um were sort of things that were put
into the language that are not object
oriented
in nature but they were fixes
to make the object-oriented language
work
and so oops we have a message in the
chat
[Music]
uh nope okay we don't you froze for a
moment
yeah i'm on campus yeah thank you let me
know if i freeze
again i'm gonna open up this chat and
put it here handy
um i think that the internet is not as
good as it is in my house actually
uh one of the pros and cons
of uh sheltering in place or being at
home
uh so hopefully it won't freeze again
and if i do then we'll just call it a
day
and uh don't bother reconnecting if if
you lose me completely
you can always watch the recording
hopefully the recording won't freeze too
but anyway um so a lot of the features
in c plus plus and
sometimes it's the first language you
learn is when you start looking at
object orientation
a lot of those features aren't really
object oriented features
they're makeshift features designed in
the language to make the language work
excuse me
so when java came around the language
was built from scratch
as an object-oriented language with
memory in mind
because object-oriented languages use a
lot more memory
than non-object-oriented languages use a
lot of runtime space heap memory
and there's different requirements as a
language on the underlying operating
system
so instead of working with the modern
day operating systems
like uh visual c plus plus and
microsoft's version of c
um and the.net and some of the other uh
technologies back in the day the
operating system itself
limited what could be done in terms of
the memory management
so that's why we had another language
called objective
c which was the same kind of similar to
c plus plus that had the same problems
on the mac operating system so it wasn't
just a microsoft problem it's
it was a mac problem as well the problem
is the
underlying operating system can't
support all of the memory needs of the
language
so c plus plus ended up with
constructors and deconstructors and copy
constructors and all of these little
things
to fix the memory issues and the memory
management problems the allocation and
the deallocation of the memory
objective c had inits and they also had
alux and dialogue and
a bunch of stuff put into the language
and objective c is also another
object-oriented programming language
that's made from c
so c had on one side of the fence c plus
plus on the other side
the objective c language and now
objective c
has been kind of put on the back burner
because
swift is more popular right now
especially for ios and for
mac os development so these
other programming languages in this
lecture are
tangents of java
and c plus plus and objective c
and they're out there and they're being
used
but it's kind of debatable in terms of
how much longer
these languages will survive for and the
idea in this class is not to learn every
programming language out there but to
get a feel for the language domains
so that you can pick a language to solve
a problem
uh when a problem arises and you're able
to be
more focused on the solution rather than
what tools the best tool
to be used
so the concept here and what you're
looking at is modern trends which is
jvm which is the java java c-sharp
which is what that's pronounced that's
how it's pronounced
and then the dot-net platform i'll tell
you that the
net platform by the way has changed a
bit in the last couple years
it is more cross-platform compatible
than the jbm
uh actually well as as platform
compatible than the java virtual machine
and then c sharp is kind of an
interesting language it's a hybrid
language between c
plus plus and java so what ended up
happening is we've got
this java platform that came out
with a true object and java is more true
to object orientation
than c plus ever was and so
we had this language come out called
java and it came out with a
java virtual machine the reason why java
was a strong language is
because we it got rid of completely all
of the underlying operating system
problems
and so you can run the jvm on multiple
different platforms
and then each one of these platforms
would support
whatever was missing or whatever was
needed to be handled
by the underlying operating system so it
made everything equal
but then it also added features so net
is microsoft's was originally
microsoft's version
of the jbm and it worked on microsoft
platforms and one of the limitations is
you had to run it on a microsoft
computer microsoft
operating system any version well.net
compatible version and it didn't work on
anything else like
unix or linux or the mac os or anything
like that
so in the last couple years they made
that network on everything else
so some of those limitations went away
because the popularity was kind of
limited c sharp i don't think is going
to be around for very much longer
it's a combination of java and c plus
plus that works on.net
there's no need for it it was originally
designed as a language
to write mobile apps for for the windows
phone
you guys remember the windows microsoft
windows phone
you may not remember it because it
wasn't very popular um
but microsoft for a brief moment there
had a store
app store and in the app store you could
put in c-sharp
apps and those c-sharp apps were able to
uh work on the windows phone and just
like you know just like the google
market
stores or whatever and uh at the apple
stores
um but the phone died and the language
doesn't really have a
use for anything i'm talking about c
sharp right now
um it's basically a combination of java
and c plus plus put together in terms of
its capabilities
and it runs on.net so c sharp is used in
unity yes it is you need a game engine
it is
um so it is still used in unity and it
is still used on some consoles
uh gaming consoles it's a very
nice because it has the kind of the
programming
style that's brief and then it has the
compatibility with a.net or with a jvm
kind of
concept to it so i flipped aside here
because i kind of wanted to show you
sort of the differences between
c sharp and c plus plus and java
and why i call it a combination
so in java we have
partly compiled code that's not put into
machine specific
and so from source code to executable
file there's this compilation process
and in the compilation process you know
we go through these series of stages or
phases you know we we saw them in the
beginning of the class we have the
scanner
parser syntax analysis semantic analysis
intermediate code generation and then we
have
and all of these stages are done in a
particular order
so c sharp does the stages
similar to java but it's compiled
very similar to c plus plus so it's in
the compilation process that the two are
sort of merged together and so it gave
us the best of both worlds if you look
at the way that a java program
is created each one of the dot java
files turns into a dot class
and each one of those small little dot
classes sits there
and the run time the jvm puts them
together in the runtime environment
in c plus plus there's just one
executable
that one executable runs on a target
platform
yeah it's a exe file so you don't
necessarily get a exe file with java and
you don't necessarily need one
well you can still have the same concept
so you can have
in c sharp you've got separate little
running programs or
things that are executable on their own
just like c plus plus
so they're target specific
and they're small and you don't have to
load all of them up into memory
you can only you know load what you need
when it's used
and have the same memory efficiency as
java which is why a lot of game
consoles and game hardware equipment
as well as other uc
uh microsoft actually uses c-sharp on
their
game consoles uh xbox
um i'm not gonna get into game consoles
uh because i don't
i don't know what's current but long
story short
it's an embedded environment for which
you need us very good memory management
and the benefits of c sharp are still
being recognized there
now c sharp for internet development is
with asp
so asp.net is
very popular and so c sharp ish
or asp is still being
used in web development as well so
java by the way is not the same as
javascript
javascript is a scripting language
that's client-side
that works uh for internet development
java can be used for internet
development as well it's an
object-oriented
programming language you need to go
through jsp
or servlets and look at java enterprise
edition
if you want to get into development work
and its server side
if you take a web development class
you'll learn about client-side and
server-side programming languages
and but job everyone seems to think
javascript
is the client-side version of java it's
not
it's a completely different programming
language and if you wanted to you could
actually take and compare and contrast
javascript with java because they are
two different languages
and javascript is supposed to be object
oriented
but you never create a class if you want
to do it for this assignment you can't
first assignment number five you can
and it might be an interesting adventure
uh
but you know more power to you okay so
in this particular case we're looking at
scripting and so c
plus plus is really a scripting kind of
language
so the modern day programming languages
are changing in the way that the phases
of compilation are performed
the way that the code is written this is
more written like a script
in fact when you see things like begin
and
end and write line this is like
scripting
uh so python is written sort of like
scripting as well
so when people learn python as their
first language they don't
understand the concept of like they're
being main
and they're being this flow control and
they're being all because python is a
scripting
as well as a programming language c
sharp is a scripting
swift is a scripting javascript is
scripting but java is not scripting
and then there's jython and cython
which is java mixed in with python or
java mixed
in with c plus plus to give c plus plus
more java features or to give python
more java features or vice verse
so modern day programming languages are
hybrids
they are combinations of different types
of languages put together
all right so this what we're looking at
is the syntax tree and a symbol table
that could be created from a compilation
process
you've got blocks of code and the blocks
run in memory
and they all connect with each other you
have basic blocks
that kind of put together and this is
really just kind of going through
this and if you really want to review
the compilation process this lecture is
not bad
i mean it's going through the
differences and the changes that are
being made
with modern day languages and you can
probably read through this at a slower
pace it is in the course materials for
this week
but we're going away from machine
code that is dependent on one particular
platform
and the trend is to go to independent
code
so machine independent code is an
improvement
because you can write one source code
one thing of source code
and basically run it on multiple
different platforms without having to
rewrite the program
and so languages like java provide that
languages like c sharp provide that
um so you can have essentially
a multi-platform multiple compatibility
source code
and you don't have to keep rewriting
programs the last thing a programmer
wants to do is rewrite the code
you want the code to last forever
and then be ported to different
platforms and the concept of porting
always makes mistakes as well in the
past
things were ported from c
to asp or to
java or to other languages to make them
work and
the trends these days is not to have to
port and not to have to make things
uh independent on particular platforms
so target cogeneration is the issue
we don't want to have to create an
executable file
and so that's something where brand new
students in computer science are all
about that
you know the concept of that exe file or
the
com file from a windows perspective is
completely outdated
but we're still running it all microsoft
development through visual studio
creates the concept of a static
executable file and so a lot of
older if you've been in computer science
for a very long time
and that's how you started developing
stuff you started creating those exe
files
all of a sudden your output or your your
your viewpoint
on programming changes because
you don't recognize the compilation or
you don't actually see the
or hopefully you start seeing the
benefit of not creating an executable
so i once had and this was um this was a
couple years back
actually um and it was an older student
who had been in computer science for a
very long time as a grad student
i told me that you know well java's not
compiled
oh no actually i'm sorry he said that
python wasn't compiled
python's not compiled code i'm like i
don't
know any computer system that can run
python
like computers don't speak python they
speak machine code
and the idea is every target machine
today speaks machine code
and the question is who's translating it
into machine code is the programmer
doing it through the compilation process
or is the runtime interpreter doing it
and so it took about 45 minutes actually
to convince this guy that
python is a compiled programming
language
all programming languages are compiled
languages
it's just you're not recognizing because
you're not looking
at the traditional spaces of compilation
and you're not understanding that there
can be changes in which
we don't have machine specific code
that's created by the programmer
and so the separation of the machine
specific
code generation is now done through this
concept of interpreters
so you need to have a python interpreter
installed on your computer
you need to have a jvm java virtual
machine installed on your computer
you need to have net installed on your
computer
if you're going to run a language that
uses
that static excuse me that creates that
dynamic
compilation and does it at runtime and
so the differences are the runtime
uh hold on one second i hear some noises
on the side of the building
i will back in one moment hold that
button
baby
how am i supposed to keep the door open
i don't like the door
all right sorry about that i got the the
door propped open i guess someone came
through and went to the bathroom or
something i will
learn to ignore it uh all right so
machine specific code
improvement so if you're
making machine specific code
for a particular platform you can
optimize things
so it's not always a good it's not
always like everything should not be
machine
specific a lot of embedded devices
a lot of embedded systems that have
specific hardware with
specific registers and memory do benefit
from machine specific code
especially if you don't have enough
memory or enough hardware on the system
to create one of those
one-size-fits-all virtual machines or
operating systems so we can go from
target generation
to machine specific code to machine in
specific code
and then the way that these compilation
phases are put together
determines what type of language we're
working with
and it also determines what's happening
in the future
so the modern day trend which is kind of
less sort of like what i was
talking about today uh was
to start out we originally started out
with machine specific code that was in
executable files now we have
interpreters that run at runtime that
convert non-machine specific code
to machine specific code at runtime and
we call that and i called in the
beginning of the course i called it
dynamic compilation
and really i'm going back to those
differences between static compilation
and dynamic compilation in static
compilation
the same stages might be used but we
have a machine specific
target targeted platform that the code
is generated
for and if you want to do that you got
to create
five different versions of the same
program
for five different machines why not just
take the modern day approach and the
current trend right now
is not make it machine specific write
the code
take the code over to an interpreter or
a virtual machine
or a translator and have it translated
on
same one set of code translated on five
different platforms cuts down on the
programming effort
makes it more generic in terms of the
compilation
but at the same time makes it more
efficient and is the growing trend and
you can actually
incorporate different higher level
languages into that
so compilation phases why are compilers
divided into phases
makes it easier for you to understand
and
some people have a hard time
understanding the concept in general
but if you break it out into these
phases it's
got you know an easy kind of format to
it
so sharing the front end among the
compilers
of more than one machine makes sense
and then sharing the back end among the
compilers of more than one language
makes sense historically phases help
reduce the memory usage as well
in terms of the compilation process
and so some languages actually in the
modern day languages are doing more
intermediate forms
java is an intermediate so java creates
a
class file it's an intermediate
representation or intermediate form
of the machine code the same.class file
can be loaded on
multiple different computers and
interpret it into machine code
into multiple different versions
that are all compatible with the
different platforms and it came from an
intermediate form so the intermediate
form just saves some steps
in terms of its ability to to use it
with many different backends and
there was something here that was
mentioned the front end and the back end
the front end of a language of a
compiler is the code going into it
the back end is the executable machine
code
and so the separation of the two
help you combine different languages so
you can take multiple front ends and
stick it into the same back end
we've been doing that for years actually
long before our modern languages
the c language does that you can write
party or code in c
you can write part of it in assembly
language
and you can put it all together in the
same back end so the front end would be
the c code and then the assembly
code if you haven't figured that out you
can write assembly and you can compile
it with c
code and you can create a exe file that
contains both
that's how most of the device drivers
and driver driven programs are used
intermediate forms can also be referred
to as stacked based languages
so stack based languages are another
form of intermediate representation
jvm the java virtual machine is going to
be the one that you're familiar with
pascal not really out there anymore
pascal kind of died
they're simple they're complex but
they're also compact
and they assemble post order tree
enumerations well you've got the tree in
there you've got the stages in there
but when they're put together it's more
of a layered
or stacked architecture to it so
i'm not going to ask you any questions
on any final exam about the differences
between these different languages what
i'm trying to do is give you a
modern day version of what's happening
in terms of the trends of languages so
you don't have to know anything about
stack-based languages and it's not going
to be in your textbook either
okay java virtual machine that you might
want to be familiar with because you're
probably going to program in java in the
future and if you take an object during
a programming class you're going to
work with java so the java programming
language
jvm uses a java api
most people are familiar with that
because they've used java
runtime or they've used the rte
java rt which is the
browser plugins most browsers have it
built in already or can go out
so you don't necessarily have to put it
or
install it anymore but you get a brand
new computer sometimes you run into that
so your browser needs the java runtime
um and then you have to do it because
something on the website is using java
um the java programming environment here
we have a compile time environment and
we also have a runtime environment
and so the java compiler takes the java
files turns it into the
dot class files the runtime environment
takes the dot class files and
runs it and so you have that executable
code that's created at runtime
and runs through the java apis
application programming interfaces
is what api stands for and so you can
have the same
bright code or the same intermediate
code running on all of these different
platforms this is linux windows
your television your toaster your
microwave
uh the java code can run on anything as
long as there's a jvm for that platform
the same java code can run on it
which it's kind of a cool kind of a cool
concept
and the virtual machine architecture
is very current not only is it for
development for testing but
for running programs you can't you can't
go wrong with a vm
so the java virtual machine here where
we've got your program
we've got the class loader that loads
the programs and then we have the
execution engine um and it's all on top
of the host operating system
all right so if you haven't figured it
out um
i'm strong for a strong supporter of
java
java does dynamic class loading
uh so the user-defined classes are
loaded enables you to dynamically extend
a java app at runtime so the other trend
we have with modern day
programming languages is the ability to
keep the language
running 24 hours a day seven days a week
keep the program running
all this time and change it while it's
running
so this is the one reason why python
is the most popular for internet
development john is also popular
for internet development but not so as
much as python is
python runs in a pure interpreter which
means any changes in the dynamic
environment while the program
program is running is picked up
instantly
so you could swap out functionality and
change components
while somebody is actually using your
program
so this is how gmail works uh while
gmail is working
uh your the server is going and getting
your messages and populating it in and
doing a bunch
of stuff for you and filtering out your
spam messages and doing whatever
and you don't actually have to start and
stop the program
it's constantly running it just matters
when you're gonna check your email
when you're gone if you have a client
side program you might have to start and
stop that
but your email doesn't stop your email
runs 24 hours a day seven days a week
and the gmail system is constantly being
upgraded and so the features you logged
and if you're using the web
interface you can notice it actually
sometimes the features
change sometimes the program changes
depending upon
you know what year it is so all of these
things can happen with ever without ever
taking the program down
java has the same capability uh but you
have to pull a class out put a class in
and sometimes it does require the server
to be reloaded
so it's not quite as pure
as and when i say pure i mean like 100
dynamic as uh python python is probably
the best dynamic out there
so the execution engine the back end
transformation and the execution of it
we have a just in time compiler we have
an adaptive optimization that occurs
because the jvm is an operating system
so we have an operating system installed
on top of an operating system
and we can optimize that operating
system to take advantage
of of anything you know that's that's of
interest for example memory management
is one of the biggest ones
so java was actually the first
programming language to incorporate
garbage collection and memory management
into the runtime environment
so if you haven't figured it out uh
garbage collection
is how we're removing components from
the
memory that are no longer being used are
no longer being accessed
in c plus that is done through a
deconstructor
or destructor depending upon how you
like to pronounce it
when you allocate memory and when the
object goes out of
scope that memory needs to be removed it
doesn't have a built-in
engine to do that java was one of the
first languages that actually built in
automatic garbage collection
so that there's a sweeper in the jvm
that goes through and picks up memory
that's no longer being used
which is why you don't have a destructor
in that language
you don't need one you don't have a copy
constructor either because
items don't get mixed items don't get
items don't get messed up when you copy
memory to memory
because the memory management is more
sophisticated in c
plus plus if you copied one item
to one object to another object
the memory is going to be corrupted um
we're not corrupted but it's going to
copy the same memory addresses so you
don't get new memory
so look up the copy constructor take a
look at what that's doing and
it's basically what i was saying in the
beginning it's creating a situation
where there's a band-aid or
duct tape being used to
basically control what's happening with
that memory
okay shared data access these are all
kind of
thread data access stack frames this is
a bunch of
everything you ever wanted to know about
stack frames i'm going to kind of skip
through that and kind of look at
uh heap the heap for example
the heaping job and this lecture goes
through java
in a lot of different ways uh it also
goes through csharpen.net as well but
not not in
as much detail it's about 50 slides long
i'm just kind of giving you an overview
of what's inside of it
um java memory used in java programs is
heap um c plus plus is about 50 50.
heat memory and then static memory
so static memory is let me just go back
to this little view here
is within the stack space
or within a static memory space of the
process
you don't need to know that for this
class the differences between
stack static or heap
heap dynamic or static heap dynamic
memory
you'll get that in operating systems
concepts
but for the purposes of this class in
c the memory space allocated for a
process and a process is an
operating system term for running
program it's a program process
the memory allocation is different than
it is for other languages that work on
different operating systems
and also different for java so the
static
stack memory that you've got in that
process space and c
is managed by the runtime stack
of the running process
operating systems concepts you'll learn
all about that um
and so it's the memory is divided out
differently
in java what we're looking at is a heap
dynamic
or heap allocation that's controlled by
the actual running program
and the object versus the operating
system and the jvm
manages that heat memory and all that
stuff i said about
garbage collection is for the heat
memory
so the heat memory is managed by the jvm
which is why we don't have to allocate
and then remove
memory in a java program but we do in a
c plus plus program
so anyway a little bit about c
sharp and cnet dot-net around
the year 2000 i guess it was 21 years
ago microsoft releases c-sharp
wow i didn't realize it was that long
ago but it was about 20 years ago
heavily influenced by java and c
plus so um
there is the question is is there
anything new from the programming
languages point of view
not really they were kind of a combo
actually
microsoft's also making it a keystone
in their new development well it's not
new anymore but again about 20 years ago
is when c sharp came out as well
i want to say that net was coming out a
little bit earlier than that
and it's basically net is very similar
to the jvm
and here we got a java program and here
we have a c
sharp program we have a static void main
we got a static void main we have a
system.out.printline
system.console.writeline
kinda looks like java sorta
yep so the net is a layered architecture
that comes with a framework if you've
looked at
android or if you take a mobile app
development course um
and you look at the android it's also a
layered or a stacked operating system i
like to use the word layered
some other people like to use the word
stack uh
basically you've got a framework of time
upon
common language runtimes you know it's
stacked on top of the windows operating
system in the old days you had to
install.net
onto your operating system now it just
comes integrated in um
there's different machine dependent
libraries and frameworks that also work
or some independent i should say machine
independent frameworks
sort of like the jvm level they give you
things like you know
vb visual basic.net and c-sharp programs
that all run on the same framework
so what microsoft did was make the net
to run with
multiple different programming languages
and so like what ends up happening is
people get missed this completely when
they install
visual studio.net and then they go in
there and they go well i got like 10
different languages i got asp
which is the same as jsp by the way for
java
i got asp i got c sharp i got c plus
plus i got vb
i got all this crap in here and i can
compile them all to the same executable
file
and then i could take and write part of
the program here part of the program
over here and stick them all together
which is what you get with c
sharp and asp actually um
the framework does the same thing as
java
but instead of one java programming
language you've got this
sophisticated framework that can support
all these other languages
and then to tell you the truth it would
have been super popular
it's a great concept would have been
super du and i'm not even a microsoft
fan but it would have been super popular
if when it was first launched it was
launched for
all operating systems not just windows
so it got a lot of flack on only being
used on windows and only being
compatible
and it hasn't been till the last couple
years that they made it so it works on
other platforms
but the microsoft kind of shot
themselves in the foot on this one
by limiting it to windows thinking that
windows was going to take over the world
well it sort of has and it did but they
should have been a little bit mindful
about other
operating systems when the jvm came out
which came out before.net
it was available for all of the other
operating systems and didn't have that
bias
so all right so we have the common
language runtime and this is
pretty much going through features of c
sharp now
rapid application development visual
development tools
languages like visual basic and delphi
very popular and useful c drivers
optimized for such development models
we have a command line interface to it
platform independence
more direct approach than the one taken
for the java
java native interface j and i
which you probably haven't heard of
either um
syntax here's your java versus your c
sharp
more syntax and you know what it sort of
looks the same
and doesn't kind of sort of look like c
plus plus as well or c
all right so java pretty much stole its
syntax from c
plus plus and the c plus plus sold stole
the syntax from
c and c and c plus plus are two
different languages
they're not the same language
so it's like the chicken or the egg
where did the syntax come from and why
is the syntax the same
and if you haven't figured it out the
syntax is the same
so it's like not a mistake in this light
set
it's the same so
familiarity makes the pot makes the
language more popular
um so no one's going to write a language
today that doesn't use
c basic syntax style well i shouldn't
say that
c uh not c sharp uh
swift and python
actually but swift is the newer one of
the two uh
don't use c style okay it's a variation
of it
so people programmers own you invest
some time and you learn a language
uh you want to be able to take that
knowledge and reuse it in a new language
so this pattern makes c-sharp popular
makes java popular because this
the syntax is practically identical so a
little for each in there
let's say sharp does have some new
features added to it that that are not
in java or c plus plus either so
but you can kind of sort of see the
illustrations here between these slides
um looking pretty similar to me
so try catch finally
so anyway the slide set kind of goes
through half a dozen of these little
examples and features
and and uh earlier when i said c sharp
is uh not going to stick around that
long it's because there's so many people
out there that kind of think
that there's a better approach to it and
i'm not
criticizing the language i actually like
the language but the idea is that
there's so much speculation that we can
improve it we can grow it
we can make a better language
i don't know they thought it was going
to happen with swift it didn't happen
that way
so you know who knows maybe c sharp is
definitely going to stick around longer
than c
plus will but
it may last as long as java who knows
and the purpose of this lecture is not
to criticize the languages in order to
say one language is better than another
they both have contributions into the
computer science community and they're
both all
all languages are sort of a result of
growing trends
in operating environments as well as the
different types of applications we have
today
you're not going to invent a language
that works on a desktop
and only a desktop you're going to
invent a language that works on the
internet
if you're going to invent a new language
that's just how it works
and you're not going to invent a
language it only works on one target
platform
you're gonna make sure that your
language can work on anything
so all right so i'm gonna stop for today
and ask if there are any questions
if we don't have any questions we'll do
the same thing
two weeks from now not the same thing
i'll have a different topic for you next
week
is spring break there are no classes
next week
for any of your classes so if your
teacher's trying to hold class
telling this spring break spring break
for the whole week
uh but i will see you i think let's just
take a look at my calendar real quick
uh i'm gonna see you on april
7th it looks like yeah next week is the
31st of march oh my god we're into april
already
april 7th is the next time we're gonna
have class
it's after the spring break
so questions comments or concerns or
anything
and i think you
oh you guys still awake thank you all
pretending
uh looks like my internet yes we are
awake okay good
well it's better than having everybody
try to talk at the same time
so that's good there's this people are
kind of adapted to zoom
so kind of same patterns are occurring
so unless you have any questions or
anything i see you guys dropping out
go ahead and drop out i'm going to wait
till everybody's out before i
end this call or end this meeting
recording will be available have a happy
spring break trying to get outside get
some vitamin d
some sun exposure i'm looking a little
pale maybe i'll be all tan next time
you see me who knows i'm gonna go out
and play some girls
thank you have a good one don't take
life too seriously
and i will see you in another week
oh we got two more students krina
and sid
oh no no sid okay that's when i type
start
are you there said
[Music]
okay i'm gonna assume you're gone all
right ciao