good morning everybody can you hear me
okay
yes professor okay great just needed one
person to respond
thank you welcome back from spring break
uh let's see what is today
today is april 7th wednesday for our
regular
uh 3-1-1 meeting and we'll probably have
a short and sweet meeting today i just
want to go over assignments number six
and number seven with you
i hope that you all got the uh
assignment number five
from before the spring break um and if
you haven't take a look at the recorded
meeting
um of the class the zoom meeting uh from
before the spring break
um and you'll get um a surprise about
assignment number five
and so today we're going to go over
seven number six and assignment number
seven
and hold on one second i'm gonna share
oops uh sign into blackboard let's see
what's going on here
uh hold on one second
oh no get this push
push notification so let's see send me
uh
uh send me a push
sorry about that hold on one second i
got a lot figuring out how to log into
blackboard now
let's see i remember me for 12 hours
uh well i can't get into blackboard well
it's a good thing
i have downloaded the assignment already
uh let me just try one more thing
okay enjoy passcode
oh one moment
[Music]
please open duo mobile i don't have my
phone with me
all right so um i guess this is an
interesting experiment
uh yeah i need dual authentication on
your phone
uh thank you roberto yes i do have it
however
i don't have my phone with me i'm
teaching a class why would i bring my
phone with me and why would students be
on their phone
during a class meeting so
concept's kind of weird uh so we're not
going to be able to get into blackboard
right now
um actually
uh you know what i'm going to try
something else though real quick here
just to see if this works i think there
i have a way of bypassing this
nope i don't so now my phone with me so
i can't send myself a push notification
and for some strange reason it won't
send me a text message either i have to
go through the duo app
so wow technology gone astray
technology uh working against us that's
what this is
um not a fan of the do authentication so
far
um anyway uh i can still move on from
this
uh let's see and if you haven't signed
up for the duo authentication you might
want to soon because you're going to
have the same problem i have
uh you need well actually i've signed up
for it um
so you're going to need to sign up for
it get the app put it on your phone and
then use it to log in
quite quite the hassle okay
okay so let's see um assignment number
five is not due for a while
it's all the information that you need
excuse me
for the assignments and for the schedule
are going to be in blackboard
i'm going to share my screen and i want
to talk about assignment number six for
you right now
um so assignment number six
you definitely want to read chapter five
before attempting to complete assignment
number six there's also a lovely lecture
in the course materials called chapters
uh
chapter five but there's also one called
chapter six seven and eight
that's kind of a short version of it uh
but for the final exam you are gonna
want
to read chapters five six seven and
eight
so four chapters so after the spring
break
what you're working on now if you're up
to date
is assignments five six and seven that
require chapters five six
seven and eight no chapter nine
uh we'll stop at eight and these are the
same chapters regardless of any version
whichever version of the textbook that
you might have
okay so you want to read chapter 5 on
names bindings type checking in scope
and you're going to answer these five
questions
in the course materials there's a really
good video
the video is going to show you um
how to answer these questions and i talk
about each one of these questions but i
wanted to go over it live
just to see if we had any questions from
you guys
about what you're going to do but also
to add just you know
a little intro to this these types of
questions
were final exam questions or similar to
the type of final exam
questions that we had in the
face-to-face class
and they were basically to test your
understanding of the chapter readings
so and i'll go over how to answer these
questions in a moment here
uh but i just kind of want to tell you
that your final exam is not going to be
in this format you're going to have a
multiple
choice true false exam that is run
through blackboard using the respondus
browser
just like the midterm so your final exam
will be very similar to the format of
the midterm exam
probably it's the worth 35 points
instead of 30 points so probably there's
going to be one or two additional
questions
but for the most part um it should look
a very it should be a very similar
experience for you and if you had any
problems with the midterm
if you send me an email message and let
me know what those were
i can improve things for the future and
maybe i can change whatever the
problem may have been for the midterm
for the final as well
um most students didn't have any
problems taking the midterm a couple of
students had the browser
time out on them or had weak internet
access
and they contacted me and we had it
reset
um so if you do have a problem while
taking it i know it's kind of early
right now to be thinking about the final
but we are on the home stretch
um so just keep in mind although it will
be online you will also have a one week
to take it in the students who ended up
with the most
problems ended up contacting me like the
night before or the day before it was
actually due
so you know they procrastinated and when
you procrastinate inevitably technology
doesn't work in your favor
so anyway so i'm going to go over this
assignment real quick here
and then uh i thought i had the chat
open
hold on one second can't see the chat
technology challenge today uh it's okay
uh i'll wait until the end and i'll
close the share and open up the chat to
see if there's any questions
all right so what are you gonna do here
you google these questions you're gonna
get a lot of bad answers on the internet
because a lot of students have not
figured out how to answer these
questions appropriately and there
is no real real true answers to any of
these questions
they're all open-ended questions for
example let me just read the first one
too and talk about that one
some programming languages are typeless
okay
what are the obvious advantages and
disadvantages of having no types in a
language
all right depending upon your
perspective and your background you can
answer this in about
maybe 20 different ways 15 to 20
different ways
and the one that way that i like to
answer and it doesn't necessarily
need to be the way that you like to
answer it
is something along the lines of
if a language is languages that are
typeless
from an advantage point of view
um only the memory needed to store
a variable for example instead of
putting a type on a variable
instead the compiler can figure out
exactly how much
memory is needed
to be required to save that variable in
memory
and not over allocate or under allocate
and it can also the compiler can also be
smart about
picking the right size but also the
right types of
operations that might be good for that
particular variable
you know it's like the age-old example
of where a student
would create a float f and then just put
an integer value in there
or a double or a string and put a
character value in there
so if you created a string and used a
string type
and you just put a character in there
the compiler would reserve enough memory
for the size of a string and not for a
character and so we would over allocate
that particular piece of memory
um now the disadvantages and i'm giving
you example about how you can answer
this question
a disadvantage of having no types
might be the fact that you can't do any
type checking
so at compile time before the program
actually runs
and you can't tell if the types are
correct
or if we're going to have enough memory
and if we
don't have enough memory what's going to
happen
so i mean is is it gonna allocate the
memory reallocate it
what's gonna happen we don't know about
that because we haven't determined ahead
of time what these types are
we're just gonna use it so there might
be a higher potential for runtime errors
so disadvantage maybe some higher
runtime errors because
the reasons i just mentioned advantages
may be conservative
it might actually be a more conservative
and
you know not a wasteful memory
allocation
okay that would be an appropriate way
to answer number one let me give you an
inappropriate way
so you know you're not doing this right
okay
don't go through it's hard it's easy
it's difficult
it's efficient it's user friendly it's
not user friendly
if what you're answering for the
question can be
used in multiple questions the answer's
wrong
for example if i say what are some of
the obvious advantages and disadvantages
of having note types
in a language i said the advantage it's
easier for the programmer
well that doesn't say enough because you
i can say it's easier for the programmer
for number three it's easier for the
programmer for number four
um say why if you're gonna say it's
easier it's just
say that well the programmer doesn't
have to type
in the actual type they don't have to
actually put that in the code so there's
fewer lines of code
that need to be written so it's an
easier task for the programmer who
doesn't actually have to decide
what they're gonna how much memory
they're gonna need to reserve for this
particular type and if you look at the
concept
of types the
uh the type allocates the amount of
resources that are going to be used for
it
so um
and a disadvantage of having no types in
a language a bad answer would be it
causes problems
or it causes it could cause a runtime
error
so if you're gonna say causes problems
or it could cause an error
or it could cause a run timer say why
so you know just give a little bit more
information
if you turn it in and i don't like your
answers i'll turn it back to you
and say well okay uh you know can you
add a little bit more information to
this
it's not right and again
you know it's try to add enough
information to answer the question
but you don't have to write a novel here
either
so paragraph one or two paragraphs if
you're going over two paragraphs
you're probably writing too much um and
a paragraph
is three to five sentences so if you're
writing more than
ten sentences to answer any of these
questions
you're putting in way too much
information and be direct
and answer the question i don't need the
background information
i'm going to assume you know what
typelist means
i'm going to assume you know what typed
languages are or what types are
you don't have to start you know in the
beginning of time we had typed
and we had non-typed programming
languages and the
programming languages they used types
are blah blah blah and the ones that
donor blah blah
that's just way too much information and
so be direct
now you'll get answers to all of these
questions
in the lecture videos that i have posted
on youtube that are available in the
class
that are in the blackboard
section in the course materials section
that i was going to show you to until
that dual
authenticator blocked me because i don't
have my cell phone with me
so anyway you know what i think when i
get done with this i'm gonna try it
again and see if i can get it by email
but i don't think that's gonna happen
but anyway um so
i'm gonna stop this share for a moment
and find out if we have any questions
about assignment number six
anybody have any questions about it
anything in there that doesn't make any
sense to you
if you uh run into a question you can
always send me an email message
you can also send me the assignment and
say am i writing enough is this enough
information and i can tell you yes or no
well you're thinking about that i'm
going to switch the share over and talk
about assignment number seven which is
very similar so assignment number
six is on chapter five and
the questions are you know
uh they're worded in a particular way in
fact actually most of the questions come
or variations of the questions at the
end of the chapters
and so if you're a smart student
and you want to make sure that you
understand this the
information that's in the chapters and i
highly recommend reading chapters 5
6 seven and eight um
then what i would do is see if you can
answer some of the questions
in the back of the chapters that are
these are variations of those questions
and again in number seven you have one
two three four
five you have five
you have five questions worth five
points one point for each question
and the same rules apply you wanna
answer it
and i wanna basically talk about number
four and number five in this particular
case
um and i'm gonna give you the answers to
number four number five because what
ends up happening is i get people that
google this stuff
and then they get really bad answers
from the internet
because number four number five are
trick questions uh so
and but you want to read chapter six
this is on again
on the data type so seven and eight are
really easy
chapters um so if you're running low on
time read chapter five read chapter six
you could browse through seven and eight
or watch the videos that i put on seven
and eight
i have a two part series that goes over
six seven and eight
and i have a series that goes over five
that's in the course materials
let's take a look then at question
number four
this is what significant justification
is there
for the and then this is the line with
the
arrow next to it operator in crc plus
plus
so if you're familiar with c or c plus
we know that pointers use a dot excuse
me
pointers use a an asterisk symbol
there's a
reference and there's a d reference and
we use a dot notation
with regular value based variables and
types
for example if i said you know
a new new peep peep dot
get name pete dot set name but when we
use
like for example a structure and we go
you know let's say that peep you know a
little peeps if we just had easter
the little chocolate pepper marshmallow
keeps with the sugar on top of them
you're gonna write your teeth out but
they're good
but anyway if you had a peep peeps go on
the internet look at them they're
probably on half price at this point
and we wanted to give the pipa first
name and a last name we could go
peep dot first name is equal to barb
dot last name is equal to blah blah blah
and if we created a pointer
for this particular structure instance
we would use the
line and the arrow operator so just so
you know what that means
that's not the answer to the question
the question asks we know what
significant justification
is there well the interesting thing
is that the correct answer to this
question
is that there is no significant
justification
it's senseless and no other language
does it
and if you've looked at java java uses a
dot
and everything's a pointer if you look
at c plus plus
you can sometimes get away depending
upon the compiler and the
compiler checks that are happening by
just using the dot and not the arrow
so in the beginning of the development
of the c language
they felt that the pointer needed a
different scope
resolution or it needed a different
dot you know because it's a pointer you
know we
need it but the thing is is it when you
when c plus plus came around they pulled
it out
and you can use with c plus plus objects
you can say you know new peep
you know my peep is equal to a new peep
and then go p
dot p dot i mean everybody uses a dot
right
and that's all referenced memory so we
have reference to memory in c
plus plus that uses a dot but you can
also use the arrow if you wanted to
there's no justification for it
and most languages pulled it out
removed it completely from the language
then nobody uses this
operator anymore everyone uses a dot
because a dot is a dot right and all
you're doing is referencing
something inside of something like a
variable
a field or a method inside of an object
you just use the dot the dot does the
same thing as the arrow
that is the correct answer however i
guarantee it
30 to 40 percent of the class will
google that question
i'm not gonna google it right now but uh
maybe
the correct answer is out there now i
don't know
um i have no idea what those other ones
are saying really because they make
absolutely no sense to me
so so that's it
and you can just write for number four
there is no justification there is
absolutely no
reason to use this operator instead of
the dot
it doesn't do anything different they
put it in the syntax but they
never added it to the semantics
it's just a useless piece of syntax that
shouldn't exist in the language
all right number five number five says
what are
oh okay now now be be wary when it says
all of the differences and usually what
ends up happening is i'll have a student
send me an email
how many differences should we use if we
do all how many
are there in all of the differences
between the enumeration types of c
plus plus and those of java like
what are all of them how many of them
are there for all of them
well again the answer is zero
zero there's no difference okay so
here's what happened
uh c c plus c had the enumeration
i'm going to assume you guys know what
enumeration type is look at the lecture
read the chapter chapter six you'll
learn what enumeration is if you don't
know that
enumerations were a very old way
of putting a symbolic constant to an
integer value
so instead of saying uh 0 1
2 for our our enumeration options we
could say red white and blue
and so when we in our program say color
is equal to blue
and that would be one our color is equal
to
red now it would be zero if i go red
white blue
so who's gonna remember zero who's gonna
remember one
or two what color it was number 59 what
color is that i don't know
you put a symbolic constant on it like a
color
cyan number 59 is cyan or it's purple
um you put the name on it so you don't
have to remember a number
it's kind of like how we all have an an
enumeration and everybody has the same
enumeration
in real life we haven't and all of us
humans carry around it
well in the united states they carry
around an enumeration
and it's translated into other languages
it's called the 12 months of the year
january february march april may et
cetera and so forth
well isn't that january is two is
february
three is march and how many people still
to this day have to come back and say
well
let's see uh february oh and april say
january february march april 4
that's an enumeration is a an
enumeration type
the months names with the month numbers
are enumeration so some people i think
the numerations came out originally to
help
humans remember how to write the number
and how to write like you know 4-16
dash whatever i think today is for
today's april so today's 4-7
uh but maybe people remember april maybe
they remember four so we have a date
that has a number then we have an
enumeration that has a
name and then the enumeration is the
name constant
okay many other examples of enumerations
out there
c started with it c plus plus carried it
over
when java was developed
java didn't have it they went what do we
need these enumerations for can people
remember the days of the week
monday tuesday wednesday thursday friday
another enumeration
can't they remember the months of the
year so if you walk away from anything
today you know where enumeration is now
you can you know use it at your next
party whatever you
got how many enumerations do you know
and people are like i have no idea what
you're talking about
so anyway trivial fact
uh so the enumeration types were not
implemented in java
because people thought you know isn't
that something from the past people
can't remember
stuff and so
actually i don't know around java 5
they got tired of listening to all the
complaints so they put the c
plus plus enumeration back into java
and believe it or not it's identical
it's identical
they just took the c plus feature added
it to the java language and said here
you go
we have enumerations now quit
complaining about it you can use it
but when they queried up there's a whole
there were a couple of articles on it a
couple years back when they
queried up how many people are actually
using the enumerations they found out
that
nobody in fact most of the people that
were complaining about it have
absolutely no need for it
enamor issues with you know the aid in
the programming of procedural languages
or for like c is an imperative style
programming language
an enumeration might help you with that
but in an object-oriented world we can
just
put a name we can just create an object
that has red white and blue in it
and just use those colors we don't
necessarily have to use a numbering
system like in the old days
so we don't really need it but it's
still there
and it was added to java and it's the
same feature that is
implemented in c plus plus and if you
haven't noticed
java syntax is almost identical to c
plus plus or c you know integer i looks
the same in all three languages
and c is different from c plus plus but
java kind of is patterned after
both of those two languages but in any
case the answer to number five the
correct answer
what are all of the differences is that
there are no differences
it's the same construct used for the
same way but now you know what
enumeration is
so usually the purpose of this is for
you to look up
and understand what an enumeration type
is and then once you know what an
enumeration type is then you can go
why do we have it what are the
differences between these two languages
and
really there's only one way
to implement an enumeration
now enumerations are kind of limited in
that one way
so if you're going to put a named
constant on a number
you can't reuse the names because if i
have a numeration number one and it has
red white and blue in it and i created
an
enumeration number two and i put red
white and green in it i have two broken
numerations because do i know is red
this red from this enumeration or is it
the numeration
from red from that enumeration i don't
know
so most languages don't allow you to
rename
to use the same name in more than one
enumeration
so they're single enumerations but
anyway um that's everything you wanted
to know about the enumeration
and a significant justification none
so going back to number four i think
they meant to
implement something in the future to
treat
those i don't know those pointers
different from the regular
if you haven't noticed actually when it
comes back to number four
if we compare that to java the only
thing different in the syntax between c
plus pulse and java for using objects is
the absence of the asterisks
we don't need the asterisks in java you
have to put the asterisk in for the
reference and the d
reference and c plus plus but you don't
have to use it for java
so if you know c plus plus java is an
easier implementation of the same
language
it runs a little bit differently
trivializing it
but it's practically the same syntax
it's just an easier version of the same
syntax
with a lot of the kinks worked out so
i'm going to have you answer number one
and number two note that for
question number two and i also say this
in the video as well
look at this up and see what it is but
you're not going to be tested on that on
the final exam
i don't get into this tombstone versus
lock and key methods for avoiding
dangling pointers
and i don't look at the safety and
implementation costs of
any pointer stuff because pointers are a
thing of the past
nice to know about the pointer used in c
used in device drivers used in
operating systems development but most
of your modern day programming languages
including python doesn't use a pointer
and so it doesn't make very much sense
for you to memorize
pointer specific locking and i don't
know
mechanisms uh only because and you can
just skim through that area in the
chapter as well
because you'll probably never use it in
implementation
so all right and uh
see the videos when it comes to the
information on the rest of i
practically have given most of the the
assignment away
so this is assignment number six and
number seven that i'm going over today
any questions on number seven
so those are meant to be fairly
lightweight in fact five
six and seven are very lightweight
assignments for this class
they you should not find them to be
difficult um
i think probably number four was most
difficult prologue
uh or scheme because people just aren't
familiar with those languages
but we are coming around the home
stretch here we will be ending in about
a month or so
um so you don't want to you don't want
to lag too far
behind you can pop these guys out submit
them and then catch up on any remaining
or missing assignments you might have
you can turn them in
out of order i do have a lot of students
who maybe have missed number two or
number three
before number five is pretty easy
if you know about the alternative uh and
number six and number seven
are pretty easy uh but the idea right
now is i want you to catch up on the
reading
so please read chapters five six seven
and eight
before the end of the course before the
final and i will also have a review
session
um probably about a week or week and a
half
two weeks maybe before the final um i
will give you
um a to-do list of concepts and things
that you need to
study and be familiar with before you
take the final exam
so do we have any questions at all
you guys are super quiet today
if we don't have any questions we're
going to have a short and sweet meeting
for today
because i'm just kind of getting back
into the swing of stuff here and
it's the week after spring break so
people are transitioning back to work
back to school and the weather's
beautiful still
so we'll have an easy class meeting
today and next week i'm going to talk
about
chapters five six seven eight i'm gonna
do a little bit of
extra coverage of the important parts of
those chapters starting next week
so thank you thank you
and i will enjoy the rest of your day
and i will uh see you guys next week
um so catch up on those assignments
thank you
i'm waiting for everybody to log off
just in case someone does have a
question
another burning question they need to
ask
no have a great rest of your day
okay
karina you good
roberto are you good oh you're good okay
good good good good
good good leaving all right well i'll
see you
miss barbara oh roberto you talking
because i can't hear you
um this is on oh yeah yeah i got you
did you have a question anything yeah
um okay i was so uh
nothing very loud and clear maybe i had
my audio turned down
um i know it's kind of late but uh for
for someone number two i i remember
i think i remember you saying that we
don't have to do all 20
of the uh oh no i did uh assignment
number two is on python
you do yeah it was not it was a scheme
one you did five of the seven on this
game
oh on this game one okay not enough yeah
but for a seven or two you want to do
all 20 because those are relevant
features
right those are good features okay
i just wanted to uh double check on that
because i haven't turned it in because
of that
there was some there's like one or two
that i i don't uh
fully understand i've been uh doing all
my other classes so
ah lazy about about that
sorry hey thanks for the info on that i
totally forgot about the authentication
yeah no no problem um yeah i don't know
why they uh
you know i just did this i checked in
you know in the morning before i left to
go to the campus i'm on campus right now
yeah and then this is the first time
i've seen it maybe they just implement
it today
it they did yesterday i uh i logged in
to
take a uh a quiz
so it was it was overnight that they
implemented it
wow yeah well it kind of sucks if you
don't carry a phone with me
yeah i guess they expect you to always
have your phone or
at least log in like when you do have it
and then check the uh
uh remember for the 12 hours or so the
weird thing is
is like you know do you want like
students in the classroom
on their phones i don't know i guess
maybe they don't expect you to use
canvas or our blackboard on in class
i don't know yeah who knows but anyway
thanks for that heads up
i'll figure something out with that and
i just looked i just look and they don't
use
email you have to use the app yeah they
do yeah you have to use it they
you have to download the app and then it
sends a push notification to your phone
yeah yeah i'm thinking maybe i can get
the app for my computer maybe
who knows um if you if you can run a uh
i don't know if running a uh like
something like blue stacks
or or yeah an emulator an emulator maybe
that can work i think that's what i'm
gonna try and do all right
all right thank you have a good day
thank you