hello everybody can you hear me
yes professor perfect thank you i just
needed one person to confirm i don't
know if i can hear you i'm going to turn
it up a little bit
on my end so i can hear you all right so
today is really easy it's the last class
meeting
it's our last class meeting for the
semester um so i hope you guys have
enjoyed
the class um today i'm going to go over
the final exam and let you know what you
need to study
and give you a little course wrap up
and the exam is actually quite easy i
believe it's quite easy
let me share the blackboard
let's see there we go i have blackboard
shared
and the exam is available now you could
take it today if you're
taking it yesterday actually you can
take it now all the way up to
and including wednesday may 12th
so the final exam must be taken by a
week
from today so you have one full week
seven days
includes a weekend i should be plenty
enough time for you to take it
um and it will need to be done by may
12th
another deadline that you should be
aware of is that all of missing
assignments so if you've
like forgot about assignment number one
or number two
or something and you're missing it you
can still turn it in
you can turn it in all the way up to
then including may 9th
which is this coming up sunday so this
sunday is may 9th
uh it's the last day that you can turn
in any missing assignments
i just did a bunch of grading this
morning so if you've turned something in
recently you should have gotten a grade
for it
if you're still missing work have it
turned in by midnight
on may 9th that's the last day i'll
accept it
needs to be graded before the final exam
week starts um so your final exam can be
taken and you don't have to turn in all
your signs
before you take the final exam you can
take the final exam any time you want
i would suggest doing it after you
complete the assignments however um
but that's um that's not gonna
preclude you from taking it um so turn
all the assignments in by may 9th
have the final exam taken by wednesday
may 12th so let's talk about the final
exam for a few minutes
here i put the link to the respondus
browser
in the final exam section because i've
already had some students contacting me
asking me for the link
and it's also in the midterm section
but if you uninstalled it or something
you do need the respondus browser
there's no password or anything but you
will need the respondus browser no
camera
no cameras required either so there's 22
multiple choice and true false questions
worth 35
points the format is identical to the
midterm
so the questions are different obviously
but the format is the same
[Music]
it's about the same length too you can
only take it
one time so you can't go in and take it
multiple times
so it's only gonna one time has to be
finished in the same
seating just like the midterm so once
you start it
and you'll have to allocate at least an
hour so that you can finish it
so start and finish in one sitting you
have one hour
to do 22 questions so it's like
a little over two minutes a question
it's pretty it's pretty good
that's pretty it's a lot of time read
the questions carefully
think about uh your answers
take your time select a clear response
it is closed book closed notes closed
internet
closed cell phones and so
if you're not honest with it you're
really just cheating yourself really
um so i suggest being honest
uh if you do click on the link here it
will bring up this
page and give you all the instructions i
just went over a few minutes ago the
test
is due on may 12th if you decide to
click on the start here i'm just going
to test it actually real quick i have to
move this
zoom thing out of the way let's move it
this way a little bit
there we go well if you click on that
button it'll ask you for a password
there's no password you're actually
going to do it this way again
there we go if you get the screen it's
because you're in the wrong browser this
is the safari browser this is
not the respondus browser so
there's no password it's because you're
in the wrong browser essentially what
that means
all right so let me talk about the exam
a little bit give you guys a feel for
what is on it also um
answer any questions that you might have
about the exam
so i'm going to stop the share real
quick so i can bring up
some notes that i have okay
so 22 questions same format
but it's not cumulative okay so
the exam does not cover chapters one
we skip two if you remember three and
four it starts with chapter five
so the exam will start with chapter five
and it will cover chapters
five six seven and eight
the only accumulative part of the exam
is that there will be at least two
questions on prologue
two questions on scheme and two
questions on python
you do not have to program there's no
programming there's no writing any
source code it's all multiple choice
but there's also no source code
questions where you have to like pick
source code from option a b and c it's
on concepts
if you haven't noticed this is
programming language concepts and so
the concepts are what you're being
tested on
so chapters five six seven and
eight prologue scheme and python
now the scope for prologue scheme in
python
is the scope of the assignments so i
would recommend
doing all of the assignments before you
take the final exam um so that you know
what did we talk about what did we do
about python and what did we do on
scheme
what did we do on prologue and it'll
give you the kind of the opportunity
to refresh your memory if you want to
review your assignments
before you can still go into the system
and see them
you want to review them before you take
the final exam that's probably not a bad
idea
you just don't have to worry about
anything from before the midterm
so there's no source code writing all
assignments are due on may 9th
now when it comes to the final exam
um i would not wait
until next wednesday especially
um if you think your internet access
might be a little sketchy
um i would pick a time in which you're
not gonna be bugged
here you're not gonna you're not going
to have any interference going on or
i don't know people aren't going to be
bugging you because you only have an
hour
and you want to make sure that you can
you know calmly
read the questions answer the questions
and
have an adequate time to answer
and not have to worry about like
distractions
um i have had students tell me that you
know in the past they were taking it at
work
or they were taking it on the bus or
something i'm like thinking that's
really hard
so my advice is uh don't
don't take it with a crowd full of
people either try to find a quiet space
to take it
okay um believe it or not that's
everything you need to know about the
final exam
the questions are very theoretical
when it comes to chapters six seven and
eight
i would look at the ppt powerpoint slide
that's marked six seven and eight that's
in the course materials ah
let's see if i can find that one
actually
i believe i stuck it in the course
materials ah let's just see this way
real quick here
uh of course of course tool no no of
course materials there we go
and let's go take a look here
i'm just trying to find which week it's
in there for you
it's pretty much of the the main
concepts that were covered
up here it is here so this one here it's
in week 13
in week 13 there's a power point called
chapter 6 7 and 8
powerpoint lecture i also go over
the videos on chapter 6 7-8 so i would
go over
chapter 5 which is names
types bindings
it's a pretty basic chapter chapter 6 7
and 8 are pretty easy chapters they're
going over features
we have control structures we have data
types
there's a bunch of really cool concepts
in there actually
i would review in week number 13
i would review the 6 7 and 8 powerpoint
um i would look at the assignment
6 preview well actually simon 7 previews
these are some
example questions but chapter 6 seven
and eight
i did power points on them uh here's
chapter six part one
chapter six part two and i believe in
the
week fourteen we're gonna see chapter
seven and eight in there
let's see week 14
is going to be the same it's the same
power point by the way it's just
repeated
but here we have chapter seven uh part
one chapter seven part two and then
chapter eight
watch those videos if you have not done
so already
that's excellent preparation so i also
did a video on chapter five i'm probably
going to say it's probably going to be
in week 12 or so
about five doesn't really need that much
of a video
uh but six seven and it will tell you um
and basically it's design
characteristics or design features
and it's talking about things like
arrays and enumerations
and control structures and data data
structures
and things of that nature um because the
majority of the exam
is on chapter six seven at night so
that's
if you want more bang for your buck i
would definitely look at these
these particular chapters
questions it seems like i went through
that kind of fast
anybody there
i just wanted to ask uh so the exam is
gonna be mostly from the powerpoints and
the videos right
correct and it's five six seven and
eight plus
prologue scheme in python
and it's multiple choice true false
and my suggestion is read the questions
thoroughly because you know
some students have a tendency i mean i
think multiple choice is actually harder
than short answer uh but some students
have a tendency to think you know not
read the question just like
for example like what are two features
that are
not part of a data structure or
something and then they go not
they they don't read the not in there or
um which ones of these are false which
ones these are true
um and so it's kind of it's kind of
difficult
if to answer it correctly if you're not
reading the question and you're not
knowing oh i want the
negatives or i want the positives of it
yes powerpoint assignments and lectures
are good yep
yep so
yep ah
study chapters
five six seven eight
ppt's and assignments
oops
now the assignments um you had one on
chapter five and you had one on chapter
six
uh those questions are pretty hard and
they're not multiple choice questions in
there they
are short answer type questions
in the old days i used to do a short
answer type of final exam
and i'll probably go back to it next
semester but for the because this is
kind of you know this is an online class
doing it through a web browser i think
multiple choice is just easier for
everybody
it's like students typing stuff in and
trying to do a chart trying to put
graphics in there it's just too
difficult
so much easier if you could just pick
the right answer from multiple choice
do we have any other questions you can
type it in the chat
or you can verbalize it
the exam is fairly straightforward
um you know
i mean the best advice i have for you is
just read those questions properly don't
rush it
if we don't have any questions this is
going to be a
super super short meeting
but i can hang out and answer questions
about
assignments i've got the final
yes have a great summer everyone
have a great summer
yes i am trying to keep it simple i'm
trying to keep it as simple as possible
and you're welcome
um it was great class actually
um i didn't have any major hang-ups or
anything
uh somebody sent me a private message
let's see uh
yeah yep yep there we go um
okay you know there's a there's a survey
that goes around
actually um you can take the survey we
don't have any like assessment stuff in
this class
outside of the midterm the final and the
assignments that's pretty
pretty straightforward
but uh i'm gonna hang out
you guys can go when you're ready um
it's cinco de mayo
get some tacos or some burritos mexican
food
um i hear a cinco de mayo's american
holiday it's not even a mexican holiday
but
yeah tacos taco i'm gonna have tacos for
lunch
yeah getting ordered in um because of
cinco de mayo what a great excuse to
have tacos
um but uh yeah this class um
we're kind of right on time we covered
all the material we needed to cover
so if you guys are good i'm good and i'm
just going to hang out until you guys
are all gone
so ciao if you're good if you're not
good
hang out or ask me questions
and i can answer them for you otherwise
i don't really have any material for you
today
outside of just going over the final
exam and giving you my
last class meeting and good wishes
maybe i'll see some of you guys in the
fall
um i don't know
classes are being taught online or
face-to-face i think i'm doing a hybrid
in the fall
which just kind of like one day a week
on campus kind of like what i'm doing
right now
and um the rest online
but uh you know
sam is good there's pros and cons
there's pros and cons to the zoom
so thank you thank you
all for attending the class
and being good students
actually this group was a very good
group of students by the way
you guys should pat yourself on the back
um i have never had this many students
turn in assignments on time
and actually finish on time last
semester
i had like maybe 15 20 about 15
16 students out of the class getting
completes and just not be able to stay
with the program
but perhaps you're all getting
vaccinated and you're all
feeling safer so you want to get back to
back
normal so all right
so i'm running out of stuff to say
so i guess i'm gonna oh there we go we
got two more people
one more person oh we're done
all right if you're watching the video
thanks for watching the video
you're going to score well on the final
exam because you're watching the video
did i not record this
crap i hope i did